<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Causa Dei, or, Counsel to the rich of this world to the highest part of the dust of the earth : to which is prefixed an humble address to the King's Majesty.</title>
            <author>Burgess, Daniel, 1645-1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 168 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30271</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5696</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15481</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12652144</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12652144</idno>
            <idno type="VID">65288</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A30271)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65288)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 346:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Causa Dei, or, Counsel to the rich of this world to the highest part of the dust of the earth : to which is prefixed an humble address to the King's Majesty.</title>
                  <author>Burgess, Daniel, 1645-1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[iii]-xvi, 128 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Joseph Fox ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Epistle dedicatory signed: Daniel Burgess.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Spirituality --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:65288:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:65288:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>CA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SA DEI:</hi> OR COUNSEL TO THE Rich of this World. To the Higheſt Part of the Duſt of the Earth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To which is prefixed</hi> An Humble <hi>Addreſs</hi> to the King's Majeſty.</p>
            <q>I will get me to the Great Men, and ſpeak unto them, <bibl>
                  <hi>Jer. 5.5.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>I will ſhow what I have to ſay on God's be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, <bibl>
                  <hi>Job 6.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Magnae Virtutis eſt cum ſeculari Foelicitate luctari, ne Illiciat ne Corrumpat, at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſubvertat ipſa Foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitas. Magnae Foelicitatis eſt a Foelicitate non Vinci. <bibl>
                  <hi>Auguſt.</hi> de Verbo Domini.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Joſeph Fox,</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall.</hi> 1697.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:65288:2"/>
            <pb n="v" facs="tcp:65288:2"/>
            <head>TO THE High and Mighty Prince, WILLIAM, BY THE Special Grace of God, of <hi>England, Scotland, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Rightful and Lawful KING!</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Majeſty!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>OLD Times have ſaid, <hi>the King of</hi> England, <hi>is King Devils.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="vi" facs="tcp:65288:3"/>
            <p>But, with much more Reaſon, it will be ſaid ſo by <hi>Poſterity,</hi> if in your Reign we do behave our ſelves <hi>Obſtinately.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For <hi>Demoniacks</hi> we muſt be, and <hi>Fiends</hi> Prodigious, if we break the dear Bonds which God and your Majeſty lay on us. Our Anceſtors had never ſuch <hi>Cloven Feet</hi> as we ſhall ſhew, if we kick now.</p>
            <p>Now that, God hath ſaved us out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> by you his <hi>Moſes.</hi> Out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> by you his <hi>Cyrus.</hi> And, from <hi>the worſt of Arrows-ſhot,</hi> by you the <hi>Shield.</hi> The <hi>Shield</hi> full often expoſing it ſelf to be broke to pieces, to keep us in whole Skins.</p>
            <pb n="vii" facs="tcp:65288:3"/>
            <p>Now that, by <hi>the very ſound of your Name,</hi> the Almighty hath ſtruck down our <hi>Domeſtick Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars.</hi> By your <hi>Magnanimity,</hi> hath made the <hi>Boyn</hi> more memorable than <hi>Marathron.</hi> And put a Hook into the Noſe of <hi>the moſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Leviathan.</hi> So keeping our <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> from being turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an <hi>Acheldama.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that, Divine Grace hath made you in very Truth, <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender of the Faith.</hi> And, you are in Act, as well as in Office, <hi>Utri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Tabulae Cuſtos.</hi> With our <hi>other Enemies,</hi> delivering us from our moſt <hi>unmerciful Selves.</hi> Calling a <hi>Faſt,</hi> far more Holy than <hi>Lent;</hi> by forbidding your <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> to <hi>eat up one anothers Churches,</hi> as they had uſed to do.</p>
            <pb n="viii" facs="tcp:65288:4"/>
            <p>Now that, after all, the Lord of Life and Strength, <hi>holdeth your Soul in Life, and your Bow in Strength.</hi> Tho, of your Heavenly <hi>MARY,</hi> the World was no longer wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy. And, tho your <hi>Martyrdom,</hi> and therein our <hi>Ruin,</hi> hath been ſought without ceaſing.</p>
            <p>Sought by the right <hi>Roman Rule.</hi> By <hi>Mariana</hi> his <hi>Quâcun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Arte,</hi> and by <hi>Bellarmine</hi> his <hi>Omni Ratione.</hi> And that, both in your <hi>Summer-Camps,</hi> and in your <hi>Winter-Quarters.</hi> Inſomuch, that, altho you <hi>never ſaw Fear, but in your Enemies Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces;</hi> yet, for our Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion's ſake, <hi>you have ſtood in Jeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardy every Hour,</hi> if I may not ſay, <hi>you have been killed all the Year long!</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="ix" facs="tcp:65288:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Great Sir!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It were <hi>now</hi> to be hoped, that the <hi>evil Spirit might be driven out of the Land.</hi> That a <hi>Sober, Righteous, and Godly Age</hi> might commence. And, that <hi>Engliſh Men</hi> might, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all Men, <hi>Fear God and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour their King.</hi> But only, <hi>that which ſtill Letteth will Let, till it be taken out of the Way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Namely, the <hi>Irreligion</hi> and <hi>Vice</hi> of <hi>Men of high Degree.</hi> Men, ſo wild-grown, that they will nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do <hi>your Majeſty</hi> the favour, <hi>to let you ſwear the next Oath.</hi> Nor be ſo kind to their <hi>fellow Subjects,</hi> as <hi>to keep their Profaneſs unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="x" facs="tcp:65288:5"/>
            <p>Men, who, like poiſoned Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, diffuſe their Venoms. <hi>From London to the Mount,</hi> murder our <hi>Morals.</hi> And, <hi>ridiculing all Laws,</hi> Human and Divine; and <hi>teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Men ſo to do; do Debauch the better inclined Nation.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,</p>
            <p>The Application of your Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Wiſdom to the <hi>reclaiming</hi> of them, is moſt humbly intreated. Inaſmuch as <hi>their Reduction would be your whole Realm's</hi> Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And, would hugely <hi>leſſen the Diſtance betwixt Heaven and this Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A more <hi>glorious Service,</hi> there is not for you to do under the Sun. There being no ſuch <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thon</hi>
               <pb n="xi" facs="tcp:65288:5"/>as Rich Mens Sin is, for any <hi>Apollo</hi> to conquer. For this Service therefore, you have as many <hi>Petitioners,</hi> as you have Subjects who are of ſerious Religion. And, <hi>which have got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the Victory over the BEAST, and over his Image, and over his Mark.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of theſe <hi>Chriſtian Catholicks</hi> is he, who doth not <hi>dedicate this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſerving Book;</hi> but only <hi>commend its moſt meritorious Cauſe,</hi> unto the <hi>beſt</hi> King in this World. The King leaſt needing to be <hi>taught,</hi> (tho he may need to be put in <hi>Remembrance</hi>) that <hi>Kings and Subjects are invulnerable, but by their own, and by each others Sins!</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="xii" facs="tcp:65288:6"/>
            <p>In which confidence, not <hi>for Wrath,</hi> but <hi>for Conſcience-ſake,</hi> he is,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Majeſty's moſt Faithful, moſt Humble, and moſt Obedient Subject, DANIEL BURGESS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb n="xiii" facs="tcp:65288:6"/>
            <head>To the Honourable <hi>EDWARD CHEEK</hi> Eſq; In ITALY.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is only <hi>Heaven,</hi> that is ſtored with lovely Creatures, better than <hi>Old-England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs, your Abſence is more than a little Grievous. So, as the want of a <hi>Diamond</hi> uſeth to be; even when it drops from a <hi>Jewel,</hi> wherein it leaves very <hi>illuſtrious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtellations.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="xiv" facs="tcp:65288:7"/>
            <p>Howbeit, in their <hi>penſive Thoughts</hi> your Friends have very <hi>Cordial Drops.</hi> They have to conſider, that your <hi>Travel</hi> is not <hi>Extravagance.</hi> That your <hi>Tranſplantation</hi> is for <hi>Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi> And, what is more;</p>
            <p>That, through the Grace of God, you do keep the <hi>rare Sobriety,</hi> which you carried with you. And, do gain the <hi>rich Literature</hi> which you went for. That you have made <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neva</hi> to value her ſelf, upon your Proficience there. And do not loſe your Time at <hi>Milan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Inſomuch that your Native Land grows big with Expectation. Expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to receive her <hi>Treaſure</hi> again, and with a <hi>noble Intereſt.</hi> To have you, e're it be long, in <hi>Parliament Robes.</hi> And, to have ſuch ſervice of your <hi>Endowments,</hi> as may add luſtre to the <hi>bright Names,</hi> both of <hi>CHEEK</hi> and of <hi>RUSSEL.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="xv" facs="tcp:65288:7"/>
            <p>Such as may make the STATE and the CHURCH your Debtors. And, not admit it to be ſaid of your choice Parts, as a <hi>Commoner</hi> of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſaid of <hi>an unhappy Lord's;</hi> that <hi>God gave the Uſe, but the Devil gave the Application.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For this, the beſt of Mothers is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in Prayers. Her Honour's <hi>Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet</hi> and <hi>Chappel,</hi> keep ſmoking with <hi>Sacred Incenſe</hi> for this. The excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent <hi>Bathſheba</hi> is thus active for her deareſt <hi>Lemuel.</hi> Hoping, that in convenient Seaſon, ſhe ſhall have the <hi>Royal Pſalmiſt</hi>'s Cauſe to take up the moſt deſirable part of his words; <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be the Lord God of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>who hath given me ſuch a Son, mine Eyes even ſeeing it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither is her Ladyſhip <hi>alone,</hi> in this Divine Service. <hi>Offerings,</hi> and <hi>whole Burnt-Offerings,</hi> do alſo aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend
<pb n="xvi" facs="tcp:65288:8"/>from other <hi>Altars.</hi> Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, he is one of your <hi>Orators,</hi> who is the <hi>Author</hi> of theſe following Pages.</p>
            <p>Pages, which, by <hi>Dedication</hi> he maketh your own; for want of better means to acknowledg his Obligations, and to expreſs his Affections to Mr. <hi>CHEEK.</hi> And the rather, becauſe he hopeth, that, by the Bleſſing of the Almighty, their <hi>Words of Truth and Uprightneſs,</hi> will be <hi>Nails</hi> to faſten, and <hi>Goads</hi> to quicken, your laudable Vertues. Which is the only Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt Obliged, moſt Affectionate, and moſt Obedient Servant, <hi>Daniel Burgeſs.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:65288:8"/>
            <head>Counſel to the Rich of this World.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Of God's particular Love, and Care of the Souls of the Rich.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Lords and Gentlemen,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <hi>THE Lord moſt High hath ſent me unto you,</hi> and my Meſſage is <hi>Goſpel.</hi> If not, let it be <hi>Anathema.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Goſpel</hi> of the great Lover of Souls. Of <hi>your Souls,</hi> as truly as of any <hi>inferior Ranks.</hi> Yea, very <hi>particularly</hi> of Yours.</p>
               <p>Indeed <hi>the Poor</hi> have his Goſpel <hi>Preached</hi> to them. But they have it not <hi>confined</hi> unto them. And it is, unto the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:65288:9"/>
                  <hi>Preaching of the Goſpel;</hi> it is not to <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation by it,</hi> that the Holy Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Not many Wiſe after the Fleſh, not many Mighty, and not many Noble are called.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moſt certain it is; that, <hi>Men of nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Poverty nor Riches,</hi> are the <hi>greateſt number of Heaven's Gueſts.</hi> But we are fully as certain, that <hi>Men of all Orders</hi> have the ſelf-ſame Invitation. For to the Feaſt thereof, we are commanded by our Saviour, to bid <hi>every Creature.</hi> And, to proclaim, that <hi>whoſoever comes unto him, He will in no wiſe caſt out!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea, <hi>ſingularly</hi> doth the Lord, <hi>rich in Mercy unto All,</hi> invite you <hi>Rich</hi> ones. His primary Deſign in giving you your Riches, is to win your Hearts. By the good things of this Earth, he Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lures and Perſwades you to Heaven. By them, as by all his other Goodneſs, he <hi>leads you to Repentance!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For, what are Gifts, but <hi>Meſſengers,</hi> ſent to fetch Affections to the Giver? And, is it not a Creature leſs ingenuous than Brutes, who is not a <hi>Friend to him that giveth Gifts?</hi> Gifts, ſo Uſeful, ſo Delectable, and ſo Rare, as your Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es. That <hi>Good ſhould be rendred for
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:65288:9"/>Evil,</hi> is a Truth of ſome <hi>little Obſcuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> But, that <hi>Good ſhould be rendred for Good;</hi> (the Good of Duty, for the Good of Bounty;) is a Truth of moſt Meridian-light, and incapable of doubt! But,</p>
               <p>Are theſe <hi>Good Gifts,</hi> convertible to very <hi>ill <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes?</hi> Are your <hi>Riches,</hi> gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, your Snares? Do your <hi>fat Soils,</hi> uſually breed Rank Weeds? Have your <hi>Purples</hi> and <hi>fine Linen,</hi> a qualitative Touch, making <hi>proud Fleſh?</hi> And, do your <hi>rich Wines</hi> leſs <hi>Recreate,</hi> than <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toxicate</hi> you?</p>
               <p>This, is as True as Sad. But, whoſe is the Fault? <hi>He that reproveth God let him anſwer it!</hi> God, the <hi>Maker</hi> of your Treaſures is Wiſe; God, the <hi>Donor</hi> of them, <hi>Gracious.</hi> Moſt apt he <hi>made</hi> them, to enable and engage you to his chearful Service. And, it is ſure, he beſtows them on you for the Purpoſe! Giving you ſufficient direction, for the Holy Uſe of them.</p>
               <p>Who doubts, but, it is by means of its own Poiſon, that a <hi>Spider</hi> is made more Venomous by a <hi>Flower?</hi> When <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> do turn <hi>Egyptian Jewels</hi> into I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:65288:10"/>who blameth the <hi>Jewels,</hi> the <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,</hi> or <hi>Any,</hi> beſide the Idolatrous <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſers?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They are wilfully blind who ſee not, that <hi>God is kind, Riches are Innocent,</hi> and the <hi>Poſſeſſors of them are Peccant.</hi> The Poſſeſſors, thrô whoſe Luſts, that which is Good, is made Death unto them. Proſperity, apt to be a Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, to draw them unto their Duty; becomes a Stumbling-ſtone, and occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Revolt. Their Eſtates, which ſhould be as <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s, Leaders to <hi>Canaan,</hi> do become <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s, that will not let them ſtir out of <hi>Egypt.</hi> St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s words are worthy of <hi>Cedar; That Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches might not be thought to be the beſt Good, God gives them often to the worſt Men; that they might not be thought to be evil Things, he gives them ſometimes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the beſt Men.</hi> In ſhort; your own Hearts do tell you, what a <hi>Price</hi> Riches are in a wiſe Man's Hand; tho they are ſo dangerous <hi>a Sword</hi> in a Mad Man's.</p>
               <p>It is granted, you do moſt <hi>pronely</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe Divine Bounty. Behold ye, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, another inſtance of your Saviour's overflowing Kindneſs! <hi>What ſhould he
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:65288:10"/>have done, that he hath not done for Rich Men?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His admirable Grace doth you the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, to give you loud Warning of your Danger! To tell you of <hi>the Sin that dwelleth in you;</hi> and of the <hi>Temptations that do incircle you;</hi> of the beguiling Serpents in your <hi>Paradiſes.</hi> And, of your <hi>Deceivableneſs</hi> by them, into the moſt deadly Sin. For, that you do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur; when like the unruly raging Sea, you do turn the ſweet ſhowers of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven into a filthy Brine.</p>
               <p>He proclaims it extreamly hard, for you to be Saved. Not of deſign to put you into a <hi>needleſs Fright;</hi> but unto a <hi>neceſſary Watch.</hi> He gives you a kind Alarm, in an aweful Exclamation; <hi>How hardly ſhall they that have Riches, enter into the Kingdom of God!</hi> To the Life he paints forth the Difficulty, in a pathetical Simile: that of <hi>a Camel go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing through the Eye of a Needle.</hi> Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing your Salvation to lie but <hi>juſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the line of Poſſibility.</hi> And with great Prolixity, he <hi>Inculcates</hi> this. As moſt unwilling that, like unwary Bees, you ſhould drown your ſelves, and periſh in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:65288:11"/>your Honey. As reſolving, that, if by any Warning, you will be Preſerved, you ſhall not be Loſt.</p>
               <p>Nor is this his <hi>Beacon,</hi> all your Warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. No, he requireth all his <hi>Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors,</hi> to be your like Monitors. Of any Mens Ears, eſpecially, to <hi>Thunder</hi> in yours. Uſing <hi>no more Gentleneſs,</hi> nor any <hi>leſs Severity,</hi> than will do you Good!</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charge them that be Rich in this World, that they be not high-minded; nor Truſt in uncertain Riches, but in the Living God,</hi> q. d.</p>
               <p>None ſtand in more Jeopardy, than Men in Proſperity. The Places of none are more ſlippery. The Charms of no inchanted Men, are harder to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound. <hi>Sampſon</hi> was leſs ſtrongly fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> than they by their Grandeurs. Wherefore,</p>
               <p>Go temper your Miniſtrations, to the Quality of their <hi>Spiritual Diſeaſes;</hi> not of their <hi>ſecular Dignities.</hi> Dare not flatter, and fawn on them. As you va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue their Lives, treat them not meerly with <hi>ſoft Suaſions,</hi> and <hi>oiled Words.</hi> And with Rebukes as cold as <hi>Eli</hi>'s; <hi>Not ſo, not ſo!</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:65288:11"/>
               <p>Take up the <hi>two-edged Sword of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> and call for <hi>fiery Tongues,</hi> when you deal with a <hi>Magnus,</hi> or a <hi>Dives.</hi> Storm them with Vollies of Divine Commands: Commands the apteſt to tear <hi>Cedars,</hi> to break <hi>Rocks,</hi> to level <hi>Mountains.</hi> To humble an <hi>Ahab,</hi> to ſhake a <hi>Felix,</hi> to caſt down the ſtrong holds of a <hi>Herod</hi>'s Luſts!</p>
               <p>Speak, as Preachers ſent from him, who
<note n="*" place="margin">The Text in <hi>Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 34.17, 18, 19. ſhould be thus read. <hi>Wilt thou condemn him that is moſt Juſt; to ſay to a King, thou art Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and to Princes, ye are <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly? Who accepteth not,</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>dares ſay to a King, Thou art Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and to Princes, Ye are <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly! Who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts not the Perſons of Princes, nor regardeth the Rich more than the Poor; Becauſe they are all the Work of his Hands.</hi> Fear not, as need requires, to give <hi>Cordials</hi> to the Pooreſt of the Pariſh, and <hi>Vomits</hi> to the Lord of the Mannor.</p>
               <p>Conſider the Rich, as Men under the <hi>greateſt Truſts;</hi> and reſponſible for the <hi>greateſt Talents.</hi> Men, whoſe Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is of more <hi>mighty Influence,</hi> than meaner Mens; and is therefore of more exceeding <hi>Concernment to the Kingdom of God.</hi> By theſe Thoughts of them,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:65288:12"/>be provoked to <hi>double your blows</hi> upon them.</p>
               <p>Charge them, to <hi>know themſelves to be but Men.</hi> And not to lift up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in their Imagination, above their <hi>proper Region.</hi> To remember, that Mountains of Gold and Silver, do not ſet a Soul nearer to Heaven, or ſafer from Hell. To beware, of taking too much State; of looking with Diſdain, and of breathing out Scorn, upon their Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeers. Overſeers, <hi>of the Holy Ghoſt's making,</hi> and armed with Power, to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their Sins or remit them.</hi> Charge them to mortify their common, but cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el Luſt; their Luſt for the <hi>pernicious Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilege,</hi> of a way to Hell without any ſtop in it. For <hi>the unmerciful Liberty</hi> of Self-damnation, without any Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction! Finally,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Smite with the Hand, ſtamp with the Foot; lift up your Voice as a Trumpet:</hi> and give them no Reſt, till they make God their Riches, and ceaſe to make Riches their God. Strain with Holy Violence to ſet up the Kingdom of God, in the Rich of this World. Whether they will believe it, or no; ſhew that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:65288:12"/>you his Miniſters, do believe, that, <hi>God is not willing any ſhould periſh; but that all ſhould come to Repentance!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>One thing more muſt be added; <hi>the divine Care of your Souls,</hi> is illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly expreſſed alſo, in <hi>the abundance of your Chaſtnings!</hi> For, of theſe <hi>fatherly Inſtructions,</hi> ordinarily, you have your Portions. Of theſe <hi>refining Fires,</hi> you have large ſhares. Of theſe <hi>Medicines,</hi> few have more Doſes. God dealeth not with you as with <hi>Baſtards,</hi> but as <hi>Sons.</hi> Your have his <hi>Rod and Correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> to give you Wiſdom. And, kindly he <hi>hedgeth up your way with Thorns;</hi> if by any means you may be kept from your fatal Folly.</p>
               <p>Thus hath <hi>God loved you,</hi> O ye Rich of this World! Thus hath he teſtified, that <hi>he would have you to be ſaved, and come to the knowledg of the Truth!</hi> And, what will you render to the God of all this Grace? <hi>Lebanon is not ſufficient, nor the Cattle on a thouſand Hills!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is no <hi>blacker Guilt</hi> than that of <hi>Ingratitude. Breaches of Law,</hi> be leſs contumelious, than <hi>ſlights of Love.</hi> If you render not <hi>Thanks,</hi> according to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:65288:13"/>the Divine <hi>Benefits;</hi> you muſt expect <hi>Wrath to the uttermoſt,</hi> according to <hi>Babylon</hi>'s Judgments; <hi>How much they have glorified themſelves, and lived de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſly, ſo much Torment and Sorrow give them.</hi> Wherefore <hi>fear ye the Lord and his Goodneſs.</hi> Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Of the Ways whereby Proſperity ſlayeth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THE Rich hath many Friends,</hi> ſaith the Royal Preacher. Yea, <hi>more than be good,</hi> ſaith every Spectator. Many, as the <hi>Italians</hi> ſpeak, which <hi>dwell at Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenza.</hi> Which be bold to pleaſe you to your Hurt, and as fearful to offend you for your Good. Prompt to <hi>court</hi> you to Hell, and afraid to <hi>chide</hi> you to Heaven!</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sirs,</hi> Your State is like that of Men in a <hi>Great</hi> but very <hi>Leaky</hi> Ship. Unleſs you continually <hi>Pump,</hi> you unavoidably <hi>Periſh.</hi> But, Hard Labour agrees with few of you. Nor can you much better hear of it, than <hi>Lewis</hi> the 11th could hear of Death; Death, whoſe <hi>Name</hi> was half the <hi>Thing</hi> to him.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:65288:13"/>
               <p>And, as little do moſt who are about you incline to trouble you with it. One ſays as <hi>Cain; Am I their Keeper?</hi> No, let the <hi>Chaplain</hi> ſee to his <hi>Lord and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies</hi> Salvation! Another ſays as <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>'s Sluggard; <hi>There is a Lion in the Way, and I ſhall be bitten!</hi> I know that a Bee gets nothing by ſtinging of a Bear. Another argues like <hi>Judas; To what purpoſe is this Waſte?</hi> It is as eaſy to make an old Man Young, as a Rich Man Wiſe.</p>
               <p>But what Friends of God, or of your Souls, are theſe worſe than <hi>Cannibals?</hi> To your Souls, what is their Affection, whoſe <hi>Silence gives Conſent</hi> to your Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation? Toward God, what can more prove an <hi>Infidel,</hi> than ſuch contrariety to his <hi>Precept</hi> and <hi>Example?</hi> Wherefore,</p>
               <p>By your leave, and whether you will or no, it is to be ſaid as follows:</p>
               <p>With a <hi>Corrupt Nature,</hi> common to <hi>Adam</hi>'s Race, you have <hi>Trains of Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations,</hi> peculiar to <hi>your own Rank.</hi> All Men have Rubs in their way towards Heaven; but, upon <hi>Oſſa,</hi> you have <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion.</hi> All our Lives, be continued Temptations. But yours be the moſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:65288:14"/>
                  <hi>multiplied</hi> ones. For, what are your Eſtates but <hi>Superfluities?</hi> and ſee you not that things <hi>ſuperfluous</hi> be generally <hi>miſchievous?</hi> That <hi>rank Corn</hi> does ſtill <hi>Lodg. Overladen Boughs</hi> do <hi>break. Bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoms of extream Plenty,</hi> ſeldom come to <hi>maturity.</hi> And <hi>overgrown Bodies</hi> be the <hi>fulleſt of Maladies.</hi> Beſides, Satan knows, that one of you is <hi>worth a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand of us,</hi> for his turn; and he accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly ſtrains to get you. And, there is no <hi>Eve</hi> but what offers you an hundred Apples, for every one that is preſented to your Neighbours! You are encircled with Lures ſufficient, if it were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, to deceive the very Elect!</p>
               <p>In ſhort; your Riches are
<q>
                     <l>Blinds to your Reaſon;</l>
                     <l>Opiats to your Conſcience;</l>
                     <l>Fewel to your ſenſual Appetites;</l>
                     <l>Bellows to your Paſſion;</l>
                     <l>Extinguiſhers of Devotion;</l>
                     <l>Bars againſt the Croſs of Chriſt;</l>
                     <l>Nets wherein Satan takes you;</l>
                     <l>Bands wherein he holds you;</l>
                     <l>Toils by which you do take Men; <hi>and</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Chains by which you lead them Captives in Sin.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:65288:14"/>
               <p>Inſomuch, that it is of little wonder they ſhould <hi>ſlay Fools,</hi> and <hi>wound the Wiſeſt</hi> of you.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Your Riches are Blinds.</hi> The <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty</hi> and Habit of Reaſon they do not deſtroy. But the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> and Exerciſe of it they do ſadly ſuppreſs. For, their ſpecious Vanities do perpetually <hi>court</hi> your <hi>Senſes;</hi> perpetually incur your Eyes, your Ears, and your Mouths. And thrô them make way into your <hi>Fancies.</hi> By whoſe quick and mighty Inſpiration, they do eaſily raiſe your <hi>Paſſions,</hi> and allure thoſe blind Powers to their embraces. Which being gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, your <hi>Minds</hi> are preſently bribed and blinded; your Underſtandings, given to be your <hi>Guides;</hi> conſtituted <hi>God's De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties</hi> to order your Lives; made the <hi>Eyes of your Souls,</hi> to direct in all your Duties; to inhibit from <hi>Evil,</hi> and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigate you unto <hi>Good;</hi> to teſtify your <hi>Innocence,</hi> or your <hi>Guilt</hi> in every Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice; and to <hi>approve</hi> or <hi>condemn</hi> you accordingly: theſe your Underſtandings are darkned by your Paſſions, your blind, but burning Paſſions; the ſmoke of whoſe Furnace puts out their Eyes,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:65288:15"/>making them either to ſtand <hi>Neuters,</hi> or turn <hi>Parties</hi> for your Luſts. Utterly to neglect their Office, or act moſt contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily to their Duty.</p>
               <p>Thus, do your Riches murder your very <hi>Thoughts,</hi> as <hi>Herod,</hi> the Infants. Eſpecially, as <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> all your <hi>Maſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line</hi> ones. Thus, they do hold you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaining your Fancies, and treating your ſenſual Appetites. Which is the Buſineſs and Pleaſure of Aſſes and Apes; not of Angels and Men. Thus they ſerve you, as the <hi>Athenians</hi> did the Men of <hi>Egina,</hi> cut off your Thumbs, and diſable you to every thing that is Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; every thing, ſave pulling an Oar in their Galley. Miſerable ſervitude! wherein you are <hi>all Fancy, no Thought.</hi> And are ſet upon your Caſh, as Swine on their Draff; without one look Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. <hi>Great Men do not know, the Rich do not conſider!</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Your Riches are Opiats.</hi> Your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences feel them ſuch. Your Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, which are inſeparable Faculties of your Souls. Which are <hi>Laws</hi> in them, and more unalterable than the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians.</hi> Are Witneſſes alſo; <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:65288:15"/>not to be made away with. And are <hi>Judges;</hi> Judges for Life, and not <hi>durante beneplacito.</hi> But, theſe, (thank your Riches) are all aſleep in your Breaſts. For, as your Inheritances, and your Purchaſes do give you great <hi>Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to Command,</hi> they do take from you all <hi>Will to Obey.</hi> Their Duſt, as hath been ſaid, puts out your Eyes. And, as it is ſaid of the Belly, an unthinking Mind <hi>hath no Ears.</hi> While you ſee not the Lord over you, you hearken not to any of his Meſſengers. If Conſcience then as ſuch, be importune and trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome; loquacious, and imperious; what Peace? It is next and immediately un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God and his Chriſt, ſupream Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derator and Governour. And its words are of Terror, greater than you can bear. Neither is there any Peace to be had, unleſs it be <hi>humbly Obeyed,</hi> or <hi>utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Suppreſſed.</hi> Your high Eſtates make your Minds too high for the firſt. And furniſh you with means to ſtill the roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Lion that troubles you. To give Sleep to that, which would take it from you.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:65288:16"/>
               <p>A continual Feaſt of your Senſes ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually does it. And your Riches do, all the Year long, hold this continual Feaſt. For, whatſoever your Eye, or any other Senſe deſires, you keep it not from them. The <hi>Rarities of the Earth, the Air, and the Water,</hi> are your <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> fare. <hi>Velvets, and Tiſſue,</hi> your <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary</hi> Raiment. Very <hi>Paradiſes,</hi> your <hi>plain</hi> Gardens. Stately <hi>Palaces,</hi> your <hi>conſtant</hi> Dwelling houſes. It's true, theſe things, tho they do never <hi>ſatisfy,</hi> do ſoon <hi>cloy.</hi> What is moſt ſweet, by frequent uſe becomes Inſipid. But, by <hi>Variety, and Viciſſitude,</hi> you prevent that. The Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vants of your Pleaſure, do take off the wearineſs of one, by bringing you another. Inſomuch, that Conſcience can never find you <hi>at home,</hi> and <hi>at leiſure to be ſpoke with.</hi> And ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving not<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing to do with any, but with your Selves; or with your Selves, but in the buſineſs of your Souls; for want of Company and Buſineſs, it falls aſleep. And what ſhould be your <hi>Seer,</hi> becomes <hi>Blind.</hi> What ſhould be your <hi>Crier,</hi> is <hi>a dumb Dog, that cannot bark, ſleeping, lying down, and loving to ſlumber.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:65288:16"/>3. <hi>Your Riches are Fewel.</hi> Fewel to your Luſts, and vicious Deſires. Deſires, partly <hi>Brutiſh,</hi> and partly <hi>Deviliſh.</hi> Brutiſh and ſordid, of things that are below Men; Deviliſh and Proud, of things that are above Angels. Theſe, make the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity,</hi> in which all Sins are bred and educated. Theſe are the <hi>Wombs</hi> that bear, and <hi>Duggs</hi> which give Suck unto all. But, never ſo much as when high fed; when <hi>pricked with Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vender.</hi> Which they always are, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in every Rich Door. The Furniture of your Houſes, conſiſting of little beſide Blandiſhments. Blandiſhments, that foment Luſt's <hi>Warmth</hi> to Heat; their <hi>Heat,</hi> to Fire; their <hi>Fire,</hi> to <hi>Flame!</hi> Flame, ſwift as Lightning, and only leſs extinguiſhable than that of Hell. From all the Elements you do fetch in alluring Objects. <hi>Laviſhing Gold out of the Bag,</hi> for ſuch whoſe Smoke doth moſt darken your Minds, and Fire en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liven your Luſts. <hi>Camerades,</hi> you muſt have few, more than <hi>ingenious Brutes.</hi> Ingenious, to ſpring many games of Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and to diſguiſe the Guilt of all, and their Ignominy. Whoſe ſervile Tongues,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:65288:17"/>and mercenary Hands, be Artiſts to dreſs your ſenſual Pleaſures, and raiſe your languiſhing <hi>Appetites. Theſe, with their much fair Speech, do cauſe you to yield. With the flattering of their Lips they do force you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Your Riches are Bellows.</hi> Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows to your angry Fires. And, no leſs than unto your Luſts; which, have not more Hell in them, than your Wrath. Wrath, which whether <hi>cloſe</hi> and Buried, or <hi>open</hi> and Burning; whether the haſty one of a <hi>Waſp,</hi> or the more <hi>Slow,</hi> but ſeverer one of a <hi>Lion;</hi> always is a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid Paſſion, always a deadly Gangrene! A Fever in the Heart, that kindles Fire in the Eyes; and if not check'd, gives the Face the paleneſs of Aſhes. Makes Reaſon drunk; and like an <hi>haſty Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,</hi> to poſt away without its Errand. And, as an <hi>ill Dog,</hi> to break out upon Friends, juſt as on Thieves. Yet this Fire do your Riches blow up. Your Plenty promotes this Anger, as much as any Deſire. For, have you not felt it? Indignities, and ſtorming Provocations, have place in your higheſt Regions. <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligula</hi> is ever and anon called a Dotard
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:65288:17"/>by a Cobler; a <hi>Belizarius</hi> is ſometimes, fain to beg Farthings. You <hi>mortal Gods</hi> are not above Contempts and Croſſes. Nay, you do meet with moſt, thô your Stomachs can digeſt them leaſt. Your <hi>Names</hi> are greater than ours; and capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious of more Slanders. Your ſecular <hi>Purpoſes</hi> are more than ours; and you are liable to more Diſappointments. Your <hi>Self-eſteem</hi> alſo, and carnal Deſires, appear more exorbitant than ours. And, conſequently, your Calenture muſt be higher under every <hi>Injury.</hi> Yea, under any juſt <hi>Slight,</hi> or <hi>Fruſtration.</hi> Becauſe no Serpents do more twine and wreath about each other, than Anger and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge do about Pride and Luſt. Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, Pride, as yours is, <hi>armed with Power;</hi> and Deſire, as yours is, <hi>edged with Expectation.</hi> By this means; your larger Walks have more <hi>pricking Briars, and grieving Thorns;</hi> as well as more <hi>beautiful Lillies, and ſweeter Roſes,</hi> than ours. Your numerous Families, are, oftner than ours, boiling Furnaces. Boiling with Wrath and Bitterneſs, and running over with Clamour and Evil-ſpeaking. <hi>The way of Peace they know not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:65288:18"/>5. <hi>Your Riches are Extinguiſhers.</hi> Not <hi>kindling</hi> or <hi>blowing</hi> up impure Fires, more than they quench Sacred ones. Opulence, is a more notorious Enemy to Devotion, than want of Bread! <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion,</hi> is higheſt <hi>Eſtimation</hi> of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty; Supream <hi>Love,</hi> profoundeſt <hi>Reverence,</hi> conſtant <hi>Dependance,</hi> moſt entire <hi>Obedience!</hi> But, feel you not what a weight <hi>thick Clay is</hi> of? And how hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, you, that are laden with it, can turn your Eyes, to any of theſe? Alas, your Poſſeſſions do take the full poſſeſſion of your Souls! Of your Minds and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories, of your Thoughts and Cares. Inſomuch, that, as at <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> there is no Room in your <hi>Hearts and Houſes;</hi> but the <hi>Lord of the World</hi> muſt out into the <hi>Stable,</hi> and be <hi>laid in the Manger.</hi> As little as they do coſt, <hi>Good words</hi> are more than is allowed him there, by <hi>all</hi> of you. And they are <hi>the moſt</hi> that is allowed, by one of an hundred. If any thing be ſaid to him in your <hi>Cloſets,</hi> the Door had need be ſhut for very Shame. The Complement of your Knees, at Morn and at Night, are unreconcileable to your Speech and Action all Day.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:65288:18"/>Wherein, he is plainly out of your Thoughts; and his <hi>Name</hi> is ſeldom, but very contumeliouſly in your Mouths. So truly ſaith the renowned old Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor of <hi>Paris; God hath the leaſt Rents from thoſe who hold his greateſt Farms.</hi> And, whereto is this owing? Why, the Prince of <hi>Tyrus</hi> is told, <hi>Thy Heart is lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up, becauſe of thy Riches!</hi> And, he who beſt knows, ſaith alſo of others; <hi>Becauſe they have no Changes, therefore they fear not God.</hi> And, O memorable words! <hi>They ſpend their Days in Wealth, THEREFORE they ſay unto the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Depart from us.</hi> Yea, when you are diſpoſed to ſpeak, you do ſay as much your ſelves; Jer. 2.31. <hi>We are Lords, we will come no more unto thee, O God!</hi> Were it otherwiſe, no Saint had ever deprecated Riches. But, without all peradventure, it is only poſſible to <hi>poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs,</hi> and altogether <hi>impoſſible, to ſerve, God and Mammon!</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Your Riches are Iron Bars.</hi> As from all Chriſtianity, ſo eſpecially from its <hi>Croſs.</hi> From all <hi>kinds,</hi> and <hi>degrees</hi> of Suffering for it. Your Salvation, it's true, is wholly <hi>bought</hi> by your Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer's
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:65288:19"/>Sufferings; but it is not to be <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived</hi> without your own. And, you perfidiouſly deſert his <hi>Cauſe,</hi> if, at his call, you do not promptly take up his <hi>Croſs.</hi> You are no more than <hi>Flatterers,</hi> if in reſolution, you be not his Martyrs. Neither <hi>can you reign,</hi> if you <hi>will not ſuffer with him!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, <hi>faring deliciouſly every Day,</hi> weds you to Pleaſure and Delicacy; makes you too tender to be blown on, by any adverſe Wind. Like <hi>a Palſy,</hi> it ſlackens the Nerves, and looſens the Joints of your Souls; makes them Frightful. And, like a <hi>ſtartling Beaſt,</hi> cauſes you in your Fright, to leap down <hi>a Precipice</hi> to avoid <hi>a Shadow!</hi> To turn aſide and take the bite of a <hi>Viper,</hi> to avoid the prick of a <hi>Pin.</hi> To throw your ſelves into <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Flames,</hi> to ſcape the Sufferings that be, comparatively, lighter than <hi>Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers!</hi> It ſeduceth you into Conceits, that the Hill of your Proſperity, is the <hi>Mount of Transfiguration;</hi> and there's no good Life on any lower Ground. That, <hi>Death,</hi> is a very <hi>Hell;</hi> and a poor Life, is a very Death. That plain Food, makes but a durable Famine; that <hi>ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:65288:19"/>Clothes</hi> be but <hi>Grave-Clothes.</hi> And not to be <hi>worſhipped</hi> by the World, is to be <hi>buried</hi> by it. So <hi>Timorous</hi> are you made by your Riches; and thereby, <hi>Treacherous. Fearful, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelieving,</hi> and <hi>Abominable!</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Your Riches are Nets and Bands.</hi> Thoſe, wherein Satan takes and holds you. He, and his Angels, cannot hurt you by <hi>immediate Impreſſions.</hi> It is by <hi>Objects</hi> without, that they work on your <hi>Affections</hi> within. They are notable Movers in your Sins, but, not without Gold and Silver Engines. By theſe, they do ſo move <hi>your Wills,</hi> as to take you Captive at <hi>their own.</hi> And, hold you as faſt as their Malice can wiſh. The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil is ſtiled <hi>the God of this World,</hi> as reigning in the deluded Men of it. But, delude you he cannot, nor <hi>obtain</hi> or <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh</hi> his Throne in you, but by uſing worldly things to effect it! With theſe, he did ſet upon <hi>the firſt;</hi> yea, and the <hi>ſecond Adam.</hi> Imagining, as it ſeems, that <hi>Holineſs it ſelf</hi> might be made to ſin for this World's Glory. This made the <hi>Primitive Chriſtians</hi> to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect Riches; inſomuch, that, <hi>Trypho</hi> the Jew, derided them as <hi>Fools, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:65288:20"/>Men afraid of Temporal good Things!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Richly your Eſtates furniſh Satan with materials for your Ruin. With the abundance of <hi>this World,</hi> to lay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mort your Care of <hi>the next.</hi> With the Comforts of <hi>this Life,</hi> to make Snares for your <hi>Eternal one. Agrippina</hi> gave <hi>Claudius</hi> his fatal Poiſon in his moſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Meat. And, with theſe things that do moſt pleaſe you, Satan doth moſt effectually poiſon you. Yea, he makes you to take his very Office out of his Hands, and turn Tempters to your ſelves. Thus are Riches kept to you owners thereof, <hi>to your Hurt!</hi> Thô the <hi>Cock muſt crow loud that awakens</hi> you to ſee it. Yet, the very <hi>Turks</hi> themſelves have a ſaying, That <hi>the World is but a Carcaſs, and they who feed on it are Dogs.</hi> Laſtly.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Your Riches are Toils and Chains.</hi> Such wherewith you your ſelves, do take and hold Multitudes to their Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. As they do make you <hi>eaſy Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phies of the Tempter;</hi> ſo next unto him, they make you <hi>the greateſt of Tempters.</hi> For, whatever their Wills be; <hi>Poor-folk, and Yeomen,</hi> are Babies at ſeducing.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:65288:20"/>You, of the <hi>Gentry,</hi> and <hi>Nobility,</hi> are Plenipotentiaries. Your <hi>great Dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hils,</hi> (for no other are your <hi>great Eſtates</hi>) are heaps of <hi>Worms and Flies,</hi> to angle for any ſimple <hi>Fiſhes.</hi> Your Cellars and Pantries do draw in whole <hi>Shoals</hi> of them. Making your <hi>Words,</hi> the very worſt of them, a Law of Iniquity to City and Country. No <hi>Examples</hi> do move ſo as yours. <hi>Tully</hi>'s Obſervation is moſt true, <hi>The Manners of a Countrey do lie at your Mercy.</hi> Your Examples, can ſet up Vices or Vertues. <hi>[Corrum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere mores Civitatis vel corrigere poſſunt, Cic. de Legib.]</hi> Your Practices do diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe Vices, and gild them with a very Creditableneſs. If <hi>a Churchman</hi> be buſy, his Reproof is quaſh'd with your Authority. Or, if an Head be broke by any Reprover, your Smile is a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Plaiſter. No ſmall Matter will make a <hi>Tenant</hi> afraid, of being as wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as his <hi>Landlord.</hi> This you know, O ye <hi>Jeroboam</hi>'s, who do <hi>ſin, and make all</hi> Iſrael <hi>to ſin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, be it ſadly acknowledged, <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Gentlemen;</hi> Proſperity, hath been all which it has been ſaid to be, unto
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:65288:21"/>the very <hi>Clergy</hi> alſo. <hi>Conſtantine</hi>'s Gift, was a Doſe of Poiſon; tho given with a good meaning. <hi>Shepherds,</hi> as well as <hi>Sheep,</hi> are baned with too high Feed. Like <hi>Horſes,</hi> we grow unruly when pampered. Except but here and there a rare Exemplar of Mortification, the Sons of <hi>Levi</hi> do become as the Sons of <hi>Eli,</hi> they turn very <hi>Hophni</hi>'s and <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neaſſes,</hi> when they have <hi>Benjamin</hi>'s Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. When they do very much more than <hi>live</hi> by the Altar, their ſcandalous Lives make Men to abhor their religious Offerings. The Heads are extraordinary, whom <hi>high Places</hi> do not make <hi>Giddy.</hi> The beſt of Men are moſt afraid of them. We cannot name many a <hi>Sampſon,</hi> but the <hi>Dalilah</hi> of Opulence hath been too hard for him, and ſhaved his Locks. Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> dared to ſay, that <hi>ſhe ſpoiled a Preacher when ſhe beſtowed a Mitre.</hi> All the World ſees it; <hi>too much Oil,</hi> as well as <hi>too little,</hi> ſpoileth the <hi>Lamps of the Temple. Strabo</hi> calls a rich City of <hi>Egypt, Neeropolis,</hi> a <hi>Town of dead Men.</hi> Becauſe ſo very many Dead, were therein kept Embalmed. And, every Ruſtick hath it in his Mouth;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:65288:21"/>that, where the <hi>Benefice</hi> is <hi>Fat,</hi> the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry</hi> is <hi>Lean,</hi> if not <hi>Amort.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, Sirs, <hi>to do you Juſtice,</hi> very few of you do <hi>this way</hi> ſpoil us. Rarely it is, that you <hi>Patrons</hi> do kill <hi>Incumbents</hi> with kindneſs. Many are <hi>ſtarved,</hi> for every one that is <hi>ſurfeited.</hi> They may be as ſtudious as the great <hi>Calvin,</hi> and leave their Inventory as ſlender as his; which amounted but to <hi>ſixty Pounds,</hi> with his very <hi>Library</hi> thrown in. Thô ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a hopeful Son of the Church be <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaid,</hi> they are very many who take their Deaths in <hi>Patmos,</hi> not in <hi>Arabia Foelix.</hi> And whoſe <hi>Service</hi> would be valuable, if their <hi>Stipends</hi> were not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible. You very well know, that, thô by Office they are <hi>Angels,</hi> by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture they are <hi>Men.</hi> And, their <hi>Bodies</hi> be not as <hi>Cameleons.</hi> Nor are their <hi>Books,</hi> to be <hi>bought</hi> for ſo little, or to be <hi>ſold</hi> for much more, than Songs. Albeit, a <hi>Miniſter</hi> without thoſe <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſils</hi> is but a <hi>Workman</hi> without his <hi>Tools.</hi> In a word; till their <hi>Families</hi> are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently maintained, and their <hi>Libraries</hi> competently furniſhed, you may not look to ſee your <hi>Prieſts clothed with
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:65288:22"/>Righteouſneſs, and hear your People ſhouting for Joy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to return to your ſelves. None of your Souls are taken from you by Force. All, which are <hi>taken by Satan,</hi> are <hi>by your own Hands ſold</hi> to him! And, for what? <hi>Poverty and Sorrow</hi> are no <hi>good Sterling;</hi> nor do you ever part with your ſelves for them! <hi>Wealth and Mirth</hi> be the only <hi>Coin that's Currant;</hi> the only Price, at which you let your Souls go. <hi>Nec quiſquam Animi cauſa fit malus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Seneca.</hi> None are ſo prodigal of their Service, as to ſerve the Devil <hi>grat is. Eſau,</hi> will have <hi>red Pottage</hi> for it; <hi>Ahab,</hi> will have a <hi>Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard; Gehazi,</hi> will have <hi>Sheep</hi> and <hi>Oxen; Achan,</hi> will have a <hi>Golden Wedg; Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das,</hi> will have <hi>three Pound eight Shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings and Sixpence,</hi> (unto that Sum of ours, came his <hi>Thirty Pieces;</hi>) <hi>Demas,</hi> will try the Market; and have <hi>as much as he can get.</hi> In theſe things therefore, in theſe is your Danger. As it was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed by a dying Miſer; <hi>In rich Graſs, laid all my Snakes!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You ſhall ſcarcely read of one in an Age, like unto <hi>Job.</hi> Who feared God,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:65288:22"/>and eſchewed Evil, when he was <hi>the Prince of the Eaſt,</hi> more than when he was <hi>Poor to a Proverb!</hi> Or, like unto <hi>Jehoſaphat;</hi> who, then, when <hi>all</hi> Judah <hi>brought him Preſents, and he had Riches and Honour in abundance; had his Heart lifted up in the ways of</hi> Jehova. The Enjoyments which uſually fuel Mens <hi>diabolick Luſts,</hi> enflamed his <hi>Seraphick Love.</hi> Genteel and Noble, moſt Men are like <hi>Hannibal;</hi> in Wars victorious, but with Pleaſures vanquiſhed. In Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, they <hi>Pray;</hi> in Proſperity they <hi>Blaſpheme!</hi> The very <hi>Man after God's own Heart,</hi> was leſs exactly after it, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his <hi>Throne,</hi> than in his Exile. Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes we have known, like to <hi>the Lamps in the old Roman Tombs.</hi> Which as long as they were <hi>kept low and cloſe,</hi> burned and ſhone with a Light very Glorious: But as ſoon as <hi>taken up,</hi> went out with a Stench.</p>
               <p>Rarely are <hi>hail Conſciences</hi> held in the contagious Air of <hi>ſecular Pomp. White Silver</hi> draweth <hi>black Lines</hi> in all Hands. <hi>Yellow Duſt</hi> is <hi>choaking</hi> in all Throats. And, as <hi>Mercury,</hi> it kills Men that come by it ever ſo <hi>Honeſtly,</hi> if they uſe it not
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:65288:23"/>as <hi>carefully.</hi> Opinion it is, that gives it its <hi>Worth,</hi> and Opinion is ſufficient alſo to make it your <hi>Death.</hi> For <hi>Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> the Canine Appetite after it, is not more mortal than <hi>Fondneſs,</hi> and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate Eſteem of it. To <hi>covet</hi> your Neighbours Vineyard, is a Sin very hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous; but to <hi>overvalue</hi> your own, is not at all leſs. The <hi>Cauſes</hi> and <hi>Effects</hi> of both, are alike malignant. It is ſaid that the Runnagate from our Saviour, went away becauſe <hi>he had great Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions;</hi> (had them in Poſſeſſion, and in <hi>Admiration</hi>) It is not ſaid, nor can it be concluded, that <hi>he coveted greater Poſſeſſions!</hi> Wherefore,</p>
               <p>Awake, Sirs, and look out! <hi>A fronte Lupus, a tergo Praecipitium;</hi> Before and Behind,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> your Dangers are great. <hi>Plato</hi>'s Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, is without a Bolt; he has falſely ſaid, <q>
                     <hi>It's im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for you to be eminently Good;</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <hi>Rich Abraham,</hi> was as Good on Earth, and is as Great in Heaven, as <hi>poor La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus.</hi> Except but Hell, one would have looked for a Saint any where, ſooner than in <hi>Nero's Court.</hi> Yet in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:65288:23"/>that Cage of all Uncleanneſs, there lived ſome Birds of Paradiſe.
<note place="margin">Uſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> adeó difficil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limum eſt magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum rerum Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tubernio, non cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumpi.</note> Your <hi>Seneca</hi>'s words are very Sun-beams;
<q>
                     <hi>To keep Chaſte in the bed of Proſperity, is of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream Difficulty.</hi>
                  </q> You may be ſaved, it is moſt ſure; yet, <hi>ſo as by Fire.</hi> No Men <hi>take the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> but <hi>the Violent;</hi> or any way, but by <hi>Force.</hi> Nor may you, Rich, look to take it but by <hi>ſpecial Force and Violence.</hi> Up then, and be Doing; and God ſpeed you. For your Eyes are Witneſſes, the moſt do <hi>ſleep the ſleep of Death.</hi> And if here and there, one of you do <hi>ſtand by Grace;</hi> yet, <hi>Thouſands at his ſide do fall,</hi> (God knows whither) <hi>and Ten thouſand at his right Hand!</hi> Is this an hard Cenſure? And is it ſaid to your Monitor, as it was ſaid to our Saviour; <hi>Thou art a</hi> Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, <hi>and haſt a Devil?</hi> I dare, in his Name, to reply in his words; <hi>I have not a Devil, but I honour my Father! My Father, of whom ye ſay that he is your God!</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:65288:24"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>To the Diſſolute and Profane.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>DEvils are not all of them equally Outragious; nor are all their Children alike Vicious: ſome are <hi>chief of Sinners; and farther from God's Kingdom</hi> than others. And the name of this ſort among you Rich, is <hi>Legion; for they are many.</hi> And, unto them I now turn me.</p>
               <q>Sirs, <hi>both</hi> Worſhipful, Honourable, and Right Honourable;</q>
               <p>You are they, who have turned your ſelves upſide-down! Depoſed the Man, and Enthroned the Beaſt in you. Who have fallen out with <hi>Reaſon, Judgment,</hi> and <hi>Conſcience.</hi> And have taken <hi>Senſe, Fancy,</hi> and <hi>Paſſions,</hi> for <hi>King, Lords,</hi> and <hi>Commons.</hi> Suppoſing the former to be <hi>Sicilian Tyrants;</hi> and theſe latter to be leaſt <hi>Dread,</hi> when moſt <hi>Soveraign.</hi> Glorying therefore in your Bodies made Channels for your Luſts, and your Souls made Slaves to both. You are the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:65288:24"/>Men, who value alike the Holy <hi>Bible,</hi> and the <hi>Alchoran;</hi> the <hi>Lord's Prayer,</hi> and an <hi>Ave Maria;</hi> the <hi>Ten Commandments,</hi> and <hi>the Laws of</hi> China; the Holy <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> and Ropes of Sand. Who mind no more <hi>Heaven and Hell,</hi> than the Elyſian <hi>Field, and</hi> Stygian <hi>Lake.</hi> Who deem it to be baſe, and below the ſtrain of your Spirit, to trembleat the Divine Word. Or to fear its Judgments de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced, before you feel them Executed. Deſpiſing all <hi>Arguments,</hi> but <hi>Storms</hi> and <hi>Whirlwinds, Flames and Thunderbolts!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Who, to the utmoſt of your Power, do <hi>caſt out of your Thoughts, him that hath Power to caſt you into Hell Torments.</hi> Who do baniſh your <hi>Omnipreſent</hi> Maker out of your Minds. Racking your <hi>weak Brains</hi> to ſerve your <hi>ill Humours,</hi> and to perfect their Maſtery over your <hi>Conſciences.</hi> To poſſeſs you of the Heroical Perfection of Scoffing at Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion! And of expoſing what you name the ſqueamiſh Folly of Devotion. Who do make uſe of <hi>Paſquils</hi> and <hi>Bottles</hi> to mortify <hi>natural Principles,</hi> and to exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larate your Frenzy. That as <hi>King John</hi> ſaid of his Buck; <hi>look how Fat it is, tho
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:65288:25"/>it never heard Maſs;</hi> You may boaſt <hi>what a Paradiſe you have found, without looking into a Church.</hi> And what <hi>undi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed</hi> Lives you have, tho they are like the Sheet in <hi>Peter</hi>'s Viſion, <hi>full of all unclean Things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whoſe <hi>God,</hi> is a Trinity of <hi>Colours, Taſtes,</hi> and <hi>Sounds.</hi> Whoſe <hi>Buſineſs,</hi> is, therewith, to entertain your Senſes. Whoſe <hi>Schools,</hi> are Play-houſes. Whoſe <hi>Books</hi> are Cards and Romances. Whoſe <hi>Language,</hi> is profane Swearing and Swag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering. And whoſe <hi>Life,</hi> (if a Life it be) is Rage, Riot, and Sleep.</p>
               <p>Who are <hi>Ahabs,</hi> that have perfectly <hi>ſold your ſelves.</hi> Reſerving no more, than the poor <hi>Ruines of your reaſonable Nature.</hi> Ruines, which are not <hi>Mutes;</hi> but <hi>loud Witneſſes</hi> againſt you; as you do know to your Sorrow. For as ſmall as <hi>Bees</hi> are; getting their Stings into the Noſe of a <hi>Bear,</hi> they torment him. As ſmall as <hi>Mice</hi> are; creeping into the Trunk of an <hi>Elephant,</hi> they make him very uneaſy. And, as ſmall as the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques of your Reaſon</hi> are, they do make every <hi>Felix</hi> to tremble, as oft as they can get an Hearing from you. They do
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:65288:25"/>together ſhame your <hi>Rebellion</hi> againſt them, and extort your <hi>Veneration</hi> of them.</p>
               <p>For railly and break <hi>Jeſts,</hi> as faſt as you break <hi>Laws,</hi> if you pleaſe; but know ye Sirs, <hi>Abdicated Reaſon is Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſtill.</hi> Neither are you able to let go your Eſteem of it, as Tragically as you do uſe it. Somewhat there is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you, which will ſtill prefer <hi>Hands and Feet</hi> above <hi>Horns and Hoofs.</hi> And, if for no other end; you would have an <hi>Humane Spirit</hi> to cater for your <hi>Brute Fleſh.</hi> Notably you <hi>do darken Counſel by words without Knowledg. The words of your Mouth are as a ſtrong Wind.</hi> But as <hi>Zophar</hi> asked <hi>a great Prince,</hi> you are asked; <hi>Should your Lies make Men hold their Peace, and when you mock ſhould no Man make you aſhamed?</hi> God forbid. For <hi>there</hi> is yet ſome <hi>Hope concerning you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Inſomuch, that, he who made you doth appeal to this <hi>relict of Reaſon</hi> in you. And ſo muſt all, who attempt to reſtore you. To call you <hi>home from Graſs,</hi> and perſwade you to turn, and be Men again!</p>
               <p>This being my attempt; <hi>Riſe,</hi> I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, and make it yours too. Up,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:65288:26"/>and ſtrain, and try, whether it be as impoſſible to you to <hi>think,</hi> as to <hi>fly;</hi> and to be <hi>moved</hi> by Thoughts, as to be <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered</hi> without them! There is (you rich Men do know) a Civility due to Strangers. As very Strangers as you, and your Reaſon, and your Conſciences are grown; yet, for once, <hi>give them a patient Hearing!</hi> Hear, and <hi>do not inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt them while they are ſpeaking.</hi> Hear, and <hi>anſwer,</hi> every one of you; <hi>Bray</hi> not and <hi>bark</hi> not, but <hi>anſwer</hi> what is asked; they do ask you Man by Man, in your <hi>Cowley</hi>'s Strain;
<q>
                     <l>Is this thy Bravery, Man, is this thy Pride?</l>
                     <l>Rebel to God, and Slave to all beſide?</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Thô <hi>Strangers</hi> they be, they are of <hi>no inferiour Quality.</hi> They are <hi>Judges;</hi> and have their Commiſſion from the <hi>Supream King.</hi> They are by the <hi>Father of your Beings,</hi> made your <hi>Guardians;</hi> and without their keeping, he will not keep you. Neither are they your <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies;</hi> no, but your <hi>inward Friends,</hi> and your very <hi>ſelves!</hi> If they ſhew you a <hi>Sword,</hi> it is to ſtop your Paſſage
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:65288:26"/>in <hi>Harms way;</hi> as the Angel's was to ſtop <hi>Balaam.</hi> If they call you out of a <hi>pleaſant City;</hi> it is but to fetch you, as <hi>Lot,</hi> out of a <hi>Burning one.</hi> They utter no harder ſaying to any Man living, than St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s to the Jaylor; <hi>Do thy ſelf no Harm!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A <hi>Lunatick</hi> is ſaid to have claſped a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the middle of a <hi>Sophi,</hi> upon <hi>Paul</hi>'s Steeple; ſaying, <hi>Come let us leap down!</hi> Nay, ſaid the <hi>Sophi;</hi> that every Child can do. But <hi>let us go down, and try if we can leap up.</hi> Mad are the Men, who are for <hi>leaping down;</hi> Men of Senſe, are for <hi>leaping up;</hi> even as high as Heaven.</p>
               <p>Yea and know it for your Comfort, Sirs! As high as Heaven is, more than a few have been raiſed up to it, by this pair of Thoughts;
<q>
                     <l>Godlineſs is Profitable unto all things;</l>
                     <l>The Meek God will teach his Way.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Godlineſs is Profitable to all Things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To all deſirable things; all, at which Wiſdom can <hi>aim,</hi> as its Ends; and which it will <hi>proſecute</hi> with ſtudied Means. <hi>Seneca</hi> brands you for Mad,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:65288:27"/>if theſe you do not know, and purſue. Mad, and as fit to be kept in the <hi>Tower,</hi> as <hi>other Lions.</hi> Or in <hi>Bedlam,</hi> as other People who are beſide themſelves. In <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> there be Houſes of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection for the <hi>Debauched</hi> of both Sexes. The <hi>Raſpelhuis</hi> for Men; and the <hi>Spin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huis</hi> for Women. And, Dr. <hi>Brown</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth, the <hi>rich Hollanders</hi> to be ſo Wiſe, as to have their <hi>extravagant Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> taſte the Diſcipline of them: A pity it is, that <hi>rich Engliſh men</hi> do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot the ſame. If Sober you be, you muſt neceſſarily ſeek, as your Moraliſt thinks,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Honour,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Peace,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Pleaſure,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Riches,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Health,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Courage,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Victory over the fear of Death!</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. But, Honour would you have, and <hi>Eminency,</hi> which is ſtiled a <hi>ſecond Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony.</hi> Not the <hi>Rich,</hi> but the <hi>Wiſe do inherit Honour.</hi> Senſuality, makes your Name as <hi>Carrion.</hi> Religion makes it as a precious <hi>Ointment.</hi> Precious, and preferrable to Riches, Peace and Life it ſelf. Life, which it far our<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lives; and which, without it, is uſeleſs
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:65288:27"/>and comfortleſs. Be it then conſidered; Is there any <hi>Foundation for Honour</hi> without Religion? Who, beſides Idiots, do eſteem <hi>Ships</hi> for their Carving and Painting? Or <hi>Swords</hi> for their gawdy Hilts and Scabbards? Or <hi>Men</hi> for their Titles and Eſtates? Sober Minds do judg of Ships by their <hi>Sailing;</hi> Swords, by their <hi>Cutting;</hi> and Men, by their <hi>Reaſoning and Acting!</hi> Say then nextly; What <hi>attribution of Honour</hi> can be made to a Man that is Wicked? To <hi>think</hi> him Good, is to miſtake him; to <hi>call</hi> him ſo, is to call black, white; and crooked, ſtreight!</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sirs,</hi> your Places of Dignity are things <hi>extrinſecal;</hi> and can claim no more than <hi>outward Reſpect.</hi> The Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of Cap and Knee, they do make your due; and but little elſe. For <hi>Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> is not <hi>Gold,</hi> tho it be <hi>Money;</hi> Stamp doth not alter Metal. A <hi>Beaſt of the Town,</hi> is as very a Beaſt, as any <hi>of the Field;</hi> and worſe, thô he be <hi>Knighted</hi> or <hi>Lorded.</hi> Among <hi>Pagans,</hi> as well as <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> it has been ever ſo judged. What <hi>Eulogies</hi> gave the <hi>Heathens</hi> to a poor <hi>Socrates,</hi> and <hi>Epictetus?</hi> And how
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:65288:28"/>did they brand a Rich <hi>Nero,</hi> and <hi>Helio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gabalus?</hi> In the Sacred Writings, <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochus Epiphanes</hi> is named <hi>the Vile.</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity had an Art to embalm <hi>dead Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi> but not <hi>wicked Names.</hi> Theſe, could never be kept from Putrefaction. The <hi>Goſpel</hi> buried the Rich Sinner's <hi>Name!</hi> But, honourably mentions the poor Saint's; <hi>The Beggar named</hi> Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, <hi>was carried by Angels into</hi> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham<hi>'s Boſom.</hi> Rich, or Poor, <hi>A wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Man is Loathſome, and cometh to Shame.</hi> But, <hi>Righteouſneſs doth exalt a Nation.</hi> The Renowned Virgin <hi>Aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha,</hi> being asked, why ſhe ſtained the Glory of her <hi>illuſtrious Parents,</hi> by her <hi>Severities</hi> exerciſed on her ſelf, made anſwer, that <hi>Chriſtianity was Nobility and Glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is true; Irreligious Men are <hi>Moles;</hi> blind and incompetent Judges. Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Wiſdom and Truth, ſtiles them <hi>Bears,</hi> and <hi>Vipers,</hi> alſo; <hi>hurtful</hi> things and <hi>hateful.</hi> Not is it to be expected that they ſhould be forward to praiſe their <hi>Oppoſites.</hi> But it is moſt worthy of your notice; that the Luſtre of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is ſuch, that <hi>Moles</hi> themſelves
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:65288:28"/>cannot but ſee it. And, <hi>Vipers</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves cannot but inwardly venerate it. Otherwiſe what ſhould make the blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and baſeſt of Men, to <hi>counterfeit</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion? None do go to the coſt, or do take the Pains, to counterfeit any thing that is not <hi>precious.</hi> And, what ſhould be the Reaſon, that incarnat Devils do not revile <hi>Religion;</hi> but as they do diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe it, and put it under the name of <hi>Hypocriſy,</hi> and of <hi>Superſtition?</hi> Yea, and as oft as they <hi>come</hi> to themſelves, they do <hi>loath</hi> themſelves. During the reign of Vice in them, they <hi>provoke others to ſin,</hi> that they may <hi>aboliſh,</hi> or <hi>leſſen,</hi> their own Shame, by making it common.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Peace and Quietneſs</hi> who craves not? But all the World ſees, they are not the Rich, but <hi>the Righteous</hi> who <hi>are delivered out of all their Troubles.</hi> Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and Voluptuouſneſs, are open foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of Plagues and Vexations. <hi>Neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected Duties, violated Laws,</hi> and <hi>inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Neighbours,</hi> do drown <hi>Mannor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes,</hi> yea, and <hi>Palaces,</hi> in Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Woes. As on the contrary, there is no <hi>Ark of ſafety,</hi> like the <hi>Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Piety.</hi> Religion makes a <hi>Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage,</hi>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:65288:29"/>a ſafe and ſweet Habitation. <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence and Repentance,</hi> do make a <hi>Muſick Room</hi> of a <hi>Priſon.</hi> The diſcreet Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle asks not, <hi>Who is he that will harm you if you heap up Gold?</hi> But, if <hi>you fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that which is Good?</hi> The Inviſible Ruler of the World, makes himſelf known by his Judgments, upon the Richeſt that do contemn him. And, <hi>Worms themſelves will turn;</hi> the Poor, whom you tread on as Down-<hi>Hedges,</hi> do not unfrequently <hi>bite your Heels.</hi> But, Earth as well as Heaven favours Religion! God loves, and makes the <hi>worſt</hi> of Men <hi>to be at Peace</hi> with a <hi>Good</hi> one!</p>
               <p>Indeed, Times there are, wherein the Lord of both, ſees Good, to try <hi>who is of his Side!</hi> And, in theſe, the <hi>better the Man, the greater his Perſecution.</hi> But, what then? Be it under <hi>Affliction</hi> by his own Hand, or under <hi>Perſecution</hi> by Men's, all is one. He never fails to ſupply Good Men with <hi>Courage,</hi> and to ſupport them with <hi>Comfort!</hi> Such, as render them rather Objects of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy</hi> than of <hi>Pity.</hi> And of ſuch, more than of any, it is ſaid; <hi>Let me die their
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:65288:29"/>Death, let my laſt End be as theirs!</hi> There is ſuch a <hi>Spirit of Glory</hi> reſts upon <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Chriſtianity</hi> in Tribulation, as well <hi>as out</hi> of it. Such a Vertue internal Holineſs hath, to <hi>expel Fears, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice in Hopes.</hi> But, be the <hi>Kings</hi> of the Earth ever ſo much <hi>nurſing Fathers,</hi> and <hi>Queens nurſing Mothers;</hi> without <hi>Practical Religion,</hi> there can be nothing but a <hi>Hell upon Earth. Without,</hi> you will have <hi>Fightings;</hi> and <hi>within,</hi> you will have <hi>Fears.</hi> Feeling <hi>the Curſe that goeth over the Face of the whole Earth, by which every one that Stealeth is cut off on this ſide, and every one that Sweareth is cut off on that Side!</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. If you ask for <hi>Pleaſure,</hi> look no further. Here it is; here it Lives, it Moves, and it has its Being. They who have taken the largeſt draughts of <hi>all Wines,</hi> will tell you ſo, and be Vou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, that the Sweeteſt and Richeſt are from our Saviour's <hi>Vineyard.</hi> We are agreed, I ſuppoſe, what Pleaſure is. That, it is founded in <hi>the congruity of Objects, unto Faculties.</hi> And, conſiſts in <hi>the ſatisfying <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the things which we poſſeſs.</hi> Nor will it be denied, but,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:65288:30"/>that the more noble the <hi>Objects,</hi> and the more capacious the <hi>Faculties</hi> be, the more ſatisfying, and tranſporting the <hi>Delights</hi> muſt be. Elſe the Pleaſure of <hi>Brutes,</hi> and very <hi>Inſects,</hi> might be thought to equal <hi>Mens</hi> and <hi>Angels.</hi> As readily alſo it muſt be granted; that, tho <hi>vitiated Faculties</hi> have <hi>peculiar Guſts,</hi> to which, very <hi>nauſeous</hi> things are <hi>grateful,</hi> and <hi>pernicous</hi> ones are <hi>pleaſant:</hi> Yet in ſuch Caſes, Men are beholding to their <hi>Diſtempers</hi> for their <hi>Delights.</hi> And, their Pleaſure, as it <hi>proceeds from Deluſion,</hi> it <hi>partakes</hi> of it. True <hi>Satisfaction</hi> and Complacence; ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing only from <hi>proper Objects,</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Faculties.</hi> When the <hi>Light</hi> is pure, and the <hi>Eye</hi> is ſound; the <hi>Food</hi> whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and the <hi>Stomach</hi> good. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,</p>
               <p>Whether it be <hi>Vertue</hi> or <hi>Vice,</hi> whoſe <hi>Ways</hi> are <hi>Pleaſantneſs,</hi> judg ye. Yea, whether Vertue promotes not Pleaſure, <hi>Naturally,</hi> as well as <hi>Morally?</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as it <hi>beſt deſerves</hi> it, it doth not <hi>moſt work</hi> it? There is no <hi>ſenſible</hi> Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure from which it doth reſtrain you; but ſuch as is <hi>below</hi> and <hi>againſt</hi> you.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:65288:30"/>Such, as hath incomparably more <hi>Sting,</hi> than <hi>Honey.</hi> And, is together oppoſite to your <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and to your <hi>Intereſt.</hi> It multiplieth <hi>intellectual,</hi> and refineth <hi>animal</hi> Pleaſures. Providing againſt their natural Emptineſs and Vanity; of which they are apt, quickly to <hi>ſatiate</hi> you, and worſe. It teaches you to <hi>uſe</hi> them, ſo as to <hi>enjoy</hi> them. To <hi>eat</hi> ſo, as not to <hi>ſurfeit;</hi> to <hi>drink</hi> ſo as not to <hi>vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit;</hi> to <hi>embrace</hi> ſo, as not to <hi>rue it.</hi> Let the fatteſt and faireſt of your Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances be looked on, whoſe Tables groan under <hi>Stalled Oxen;</hi> and the Countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of ſuch, whoſe Feaſt is a <hi>Dinner of Herbs.</hi> Preſently, it ſhall be ſeen, in whoſe Faces the <hi>Oil of Joy</hi> doth moſt ſhine. Boaſt not of your <hi>Sports</hi> and Diverſions; what of them is <hi>Moderate,</hi> Religion al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows. And whatever is more, doth not <hi>recreate,</hi> but <hi>waſte</hi> you. Glory not in your <hi>groſſer Shames;</hi> like, <hi>Claudius</hi> his Muſhrooms, tho Pleaſant, you do know they are Poiſonous. Like the ſtately Horſe of <hi>Cn. Seius,</hi> they are attended with this miſchief; that, <hi>whoever has them is ſure to ſuffer by them.</hi> Their luſcious Honey, breeds a <hi>Choler</hi> ſo
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:65288:31"/>deadly. Diſſoluteneſs was never with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Vultures on its Liver.</hi> But, the Sun will want Light, and the Sea Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, when Religion's deſtitute of Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure! For,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repentance</hi> it ſelf, <hi>Self-denial,</hi> and <hi>Mortification,</hi> are a very <hi>Canaan. There's Milk and Honey flowing</hi> in them, as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle as you think it. Becauſe, the Vices that made them <hi>diſagreeable,</hi> being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved; Mens <hi>Natures</hi> being changed, and <hi>Faculties</hi> rectified; the <hi>Diſproportion</hi> is removed, and an <hi>Agreeableneſs</hi> is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced. What? Is it not Pleaſure to the <hi>ſound</hi> Man to Walk; tho it was Torture to him when <hi>Lame?</hi> Is it not gladly that Men <hi>keep the Cup from their Mouths,</hi> when they are thoroughly cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of their <hi>Dropſies? In the midſt of Laughter, your Hearts are ſorrowful:</hi> but, in the <hi>midſt of Sorrows,</hi> Penitents Hearts are <hi>joyful.</hi> Yet, if it were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, a Wiſe Man would chooſe to bear the Pain of his <hi>Medicine,</hi> rather than of his <hi>Diſeaſe!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Are many <hi>pretenders to Sanctity,</hi> very <hi>ſowre?</hi> Many, who <hi>are thought to be Religious,</hi> bitterly <hi>moroſe?</hi> What then?
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:65288:31"/>So are Multitudes of you, who are Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religious. And, all who underſtand their Religion or themſelves, will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg; that, it is not <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> but the <hi>want of it,</hi> that gives Men their <hi>Melancholy.</hi> For, they cannot but know; that Chearfulneſs is both a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> which Divine Bounty beſtows on the Religious; and a <hi>Duty,</hi> which Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Wiſdom requires from them. In a word, ſuppoſe Vice to be as pleaſant as ever it was conceited; he that leaves Vertue for it, he leaves the <hi>Sun</hi> for a <hi>Gloworm,</hi> and a <hi>Canaan</hi> for <hi>Cabul!</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Are <hi>Riches</hi> of any account with you? Or, hath their <hi>Familiarity bred Contempt?</hi> If thoſe Hedges, which keep you from being trampled on by your Neighbours, be in much requeſt, pleaſe you to conſider; <hi>Godlineſs hath the Promiſe of the Life that now is.</hi> And, <hi>in its Left Hand are Riches.</hi> i. e. The <hi>Poſſeſſion,</hi> and uſe of this World's Goods, and <hi>Contentment</hi> with them! For, a <hi>Man</hi> is no more enriched with them, than a <hi>Cheſt</hi> is, if he doth but <hi>poſſeſs,</hi> and not <hi>uſe them.</hi> And, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> without <hi>Content,</hi> is as bad as <hi>Poſſeſſion</hi> without
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:65288:32"/>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe;</hi> Poverty it ſelf can be no poorer, than the Man who has not ſet a limit to his Deſire. But, Religion it is, that teaches the true Art of <hi>Getting</hi> and <hi>Keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> and no leſs of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſing,</hi> and <hi>Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> your Portion under the Sun. Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuality brings to a Morſel of Bread, and clothes a voluptuous Heir with Rags. Accordingly, for the moſt part you do ſee, Families, Cities, Nations, the moſt <hi>Religious,</hi> to be the moſt <hi>Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous.</hi> The moſt <hi>illuſtriouſly</hi> and <hi>durably</hi> Proſperous. <hi>Fartheſt from bare Feet, and Wooden Shooes.</hi> Richeſt themſelves, their Children, and their Childrens Children!</p>
               <p>Is Religion <hi>open-handed and liberal?</hi> Yes, and its Liberality is a <hi>laying up Treaſure in the ſafeſt Bank.</hi> A <hi>lending</hi> it out, upon the beſt Intereſt. <hi>Making Friends</hi> in the Court of Heaven with it; and making the <hi>continual Feaſt</hi> of a good Conſcience with it. Which, doth as little tend to Poverty, as ſcattering of <hi>rich Seed</hi> in the moſt <hi>fertile Soil!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Doth Vice appear a <hi>plain way</hi> to O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulence? It doth ſo; Sordid Living, Fraud, and Oppreſſion, are the <hi>beaten
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:65288:32"/>Road,</hi> and do ſeem to be the <hi>Direct</hi> one: But they are the quite contrary. For, <hi>commonly,</hi> they do make Poor; and, <hi>laſtingly,</hi> they do never make Rich. Penury, <hi>ſtarves</hi> a Thouſand, for every one that it does <hi>fatten.</hi> Fraud, is a <hi>Partridg</hi> that ſits upon Subventaneous Eggs, and hatcheth not. Or if otherwiſe, the <hi>infamous Brood</hi> is but ſhort liv'd. The Gain of the Oppreſſor, haſtens to the <hi>Collectors for the Poor.</hi> Oftime's Mens <hi>Malice,</hi> or <hi>Juſtice,</hi> but always Divine <hi>Vengeance,</hi> cruſheth all three. And, let the <hi>Mines</hi> of one <hi>India,</hi> and the <hi>Spices</hi> of the other, be gained by a <hi>looſe</hi> Man, he ſhall ſtill be a <hi>poor</hi> One! But,</p>
               <p>It will be asked; And are not the Communion of Saints <hi>the Poor of this World,</hi> alſo? The anſwer is eaſy. <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratively,</hi> they are Poor; of lower Condition, than you whoſe <hi>abundance</hi> is generally your <hi>Deſtruction.</hi> But, <hi>abſolutely</hi> they are Rich. For, their <hi>little is Good, and better than your great Riches.</hi> Their <hi>Appetites,</hi> are <hi>Health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful;</hi> yours, are <hi>Canine,</hi> and <hi>Dropical.</hi> Their <hi>Enough</hi> is a <hi>Feaſt;</hi> and your
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:65288:33"/>
                  <hi>Feaſts</hi> are not Enough. They are as <hi>Having nothing, yet, Poſſeſſing all Things.</hi> And, beſides; <hi>the Poverty of Good Men, is not always owing to their Goodneſs.</hi> Defect of <hi>Diligence,</hi> and of <hi>Providence,</hi> and of various <hi>Duties,</hi> brings them into their Straits. Nor would they be ſo <hi>needy,</hi> if they were more <hi>holy. Drowſineſs</hi> bringeth ſome to their Rags. And, prevailing <hi>Pride,</hi> giveth others a Fall. Rarely it is, that <hi>Saints</hi> do want <hi>Neceſſaries;</hi> and that they lay the Blame on any thing, ſo much as on their <hi>Sin,</hi> when they do want them!</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Health,</hi> the Life of Life, muſt needs be a Pearl, and precious with you. And, will you nor believe your Eyes? Or, can you chuſe but ſee, Religion gives <hi>Health to the Navel, and Marrow to the Bones?</hi> In its Hand, is the <hi>length of Days, with the Sweetneſs of them. Youth,</hi> it beautifies, and ſweetens; and, it makes the moſt, and the beſt, of <hi>Old Age!</hi> Puts a rare Balſam into all Blood. Mortifies the <hi>VICE,</hi> that by natural Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacy works Diſeaſe. Prevents <hi>wild Paſſions</hi> of Mind, and all <hi>intemperance</hi> of Body; which give the Humours a
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:65288:33"/>Ferment, that ſometimes createth <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Sickneſs;</hi> and always diſpoſeth for <hi>future.</hi> A Chearful Mind it imparts, which <hi>doeth good like a Medicine.</hi> And if any ſuch be, is a Catholicon, both for <hi>Cure</hi> and <hi>Prevention.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All Experience doth verify this The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ory. The beſt Learned King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> makes his Appeal. <hi>Who hath Wo? Who hath Sorrow? Who hath redneſs of Eyes? They that tarry long at the Wine.</hi> In the Old Teſtament, he was the <hi>Meekeſt Man,</hi> whoſe Eye, when Old, was not Dim; and his Natural Force was not abated. In the New Teſtament, he was the <hi>Diſciple, whoſe Thoughts, and Writings ran all upon Divine Love,</hi> who enjoyed a more vigorous Old Age than his Brethren. All Ages are witneſſes, how generally, <hi>vitious</hi> Lives are <hi>ſhort</hi> Ones. How <hi>Surfeits and Debaucheries</hi> inflame Blood, ſpend Spirits, and <hi>cut Lives in halves.</hi> You do know, that much will not be given you, for a Leaſe of a Lewd Man's Life! <hi>Temperance is the beſt Phyſick,</hi> ſaith Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon.</hi> And <hi>the Precepts of Chriſt well obſerved, would prevent as many Diſeaſes as his
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:65288:34"/>Miracles cured;</hi> ſaith grave Mr. <hi>Lukin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Courage,</hi> to look dangers in the Face, is a covetable Excellence. This World is a <hi>rough Sea.</hi> The viciſſitudes of <hi>Calm and Storm,</hi> are as conſtant as thoſe of <hi>Night and Day!</hi> And it is an ill thing to be without this <hi>Anchor,</hi> when Billows do roar. But, except a <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious one,</hi> there is no Spirit of <hi>Boldneſs,</hi> and of a <hi>ſound Mind.</hi> It is true, a <hi>Wild Man</hi> may have the Metal of a <hi>Blind Horſe.</hi> Yet, the moſt of them do <hi>fear</hi> the Deity in a Tempeſt, which they <hi>deny</hi> in a ſtill Weather. And, it's only the <hi>Righteous Man,</hi> who <hi>is bold as a Lion,</hi> i. e. with a Strength and Sagacity ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to his ſafety. Vice, raiſeth Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults in your Minds; and cannot lay them. It is a thing too <hi>exorbitant,</hi> to be other than <hi>impotent.</hi> Religion, as it is a Heavenly Wiſdom and Strength, to <hi>prevent</hi> Cauſes of diſtracting Fear; ſo it carries in it a Power to overrule the blind Paſſions; which otherwiſe, will diſtract us <hi>without any Cauſe.</hi> Vice doth darken, deform, and debilitate your Spirit. Religion, enlarges your Mind, exalts your Wills, eradicates your baſe
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:65288:34"/>Paſſions. Maketh your Souls to bear the change of <hi>Affairs,</hi> as a ſound Body doth the change of <hi>Weathers;</hi> without much Prejudice and Impatience. For, (what an ill Man can never be) <hi>a Good Man is, ſatisfied from himſelf. His Heart not condemning him, he hath Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence toward God!</hi> A Confidence, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled by nothing but the <hi>beatifical Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi> And, ſuch as gives the ſublimeſt Comforts in the loweſt Conditions. Whereas, in all ſuch, wicked Mens <hi>Fears</hi> do uſe to be proportionable unto their <hi>Guilts.</hi> It is certain, that a <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laxy</hi> was never found in their <hi>Globe. Furies,</hi> in the <hi>Pagan-dialect,</hi> do haunt and ſcourge them. <hi>Terrors are upon them,</hi> as the Sacred <hi>Scripture</hi> ſpeaks; <hi>Darkneſs is hid in their ſecret Places; a Fire not blown ſhall conſume them.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wit</hi> and <hi>Courage,</hi> are the things, whereof vicious Men do ſingularly make their Boaſts. As thô their Minds were the Cleareſt, and their Hearts the Stou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt of any. But, alas, no <hi>Geeſe</hi> are ſo filly, no <hi>Hares</hi> of ſuch Puſillanimity. Where is their great <hi>Wit,</hi> who know
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:65288:35"/>nothing of their true <hi>Intereſt?</hi> And do purſue no higher Delights, than the inglorious ones of Swine and Goats. Proud of their <hi>fat Quails,</hi> and not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of their <hi>famiſhed Souls.</hi> Where is their <hi>Valour,</hi> who fear and fly from Vertue's warfare? Tho they muſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer a preſent Hell, and a Future, for their running from it. Who dare not <hi>ſay Nay</hi> to a Luſt, or to a looſe Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; no, tho they bid them to run up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Pikes of their Conſcience,</hi> and the <hi>Mouth of Heaven's Cannon,</hi> and upon <hi>more Deaths than one!</hi> Their Wit and <hi>Courage,</hi> if they muſt be ſaid to have either, are juſt like an Ulcer; <hi>the big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger the worſe.</hi> Being no other than <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes,</hi> and <hi>Reproaches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. Finally, is <hi>Happineſs in the next World</hi> deſired? you have no <hi>Lucid inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val</hi> in this World, but without doubt it is ſo. For, tho, while you are dozed, you may dream; and when beſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waked, you may <hi>wiſh</hi> there were no Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture State; you are not able to diſpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs your ſelves of <hi>the Belief,</hi> that there is one! <hi>Noctu &amp; Sibi,</hi> ſaith <hi>Seneca;</hi> In the Night, and when you are Alone;
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:65288:35"/>when you, and your Selves, do, and muſt, come together; you cannot think <hi>Atheiſts</hi> to be <hi>Orthodox,</hi> and <hi>Religious</hi> Men to be <hi>Fanaticks.</hi> No more than you can think the <hi>Priſoners in Bedlam</hi> to be the <hi>Sages</hi> of the City, and the <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants</hi> upon the <hi>Exchange</hi> to be the <hi>Idi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots and Lunaticks. Mentiuntur qi di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunt,</hi> ſaith the Pagan Eccleſiaſt, <hi>A Lie will not choak ſuch as ſay that they think there's no God, and no Life to come!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sirs, <hi>Is there any where a Man, but there is a Conſcience?</hi> Does any one <hi>act,</hi> and not <hi>reflect</hi> upon his Actions? Is there ever <hi>a Party,</hi> but what is his own <hi>Judg</hi> too? And,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Can there be a Conſcience without a Law?</hi> How come Men to make Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of any thing, if they be under no Law or <hi>Obligation?</hi> And, why ſhould they, if they be accountable to no <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority?</hi> Conſcience, without <hi>Law,</hi> is of no <hi>Force.</hi> And, can you tell,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is a Law without a Sanction?</hi> Without a Confirmation by <hi>Rewards</hi> and <hi>Penalties.</hi> What is a Law when diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>armed of this? What is it more than the Sign of a <hi>George on Horſeback</hi> over
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:65288:36"/>a Door, which neither commands any Body in, or keeps any one out? <hi>Law,</hi> and <hi>Puniſhment</hi> are Relatives; and mutually connote each other, in the common Senſe of all the World. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever <hi>Precepts</hi> be the Rule of Subjects Duty, <hi>Sanctions</hi> are the Rules of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Proceſs. And, doubt you but that,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Sanction implies a Judg?</hi> A Judg, without whom, <hi>Precept</hi> and <hi>Sanction</hi> were vain. And might be diſregarded, without <hi>Loſs,</hi> or <hi>Hazard.</hi> But, ſay al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If there be a Judg, muſt there not be a Judgment-Day?</hi> A Day of ſolemn <hi>Trial,</hi> and final <hi>Judgment.</hi> Wherein, he who now <hi>rules</hi> the World with Patience, will <hi>judg</hi> it in Righteouſneſs? Who can wink ſo cloſe, but he muſt ſee this?</p>
               <p>But, <hi>what, if the Doctrine of this Doomſ-day, were of any <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncertainty?</hi> What, if it did admit of <hi>Queſtion,</hi> and were no more than a <hi>probable Opinion?</hi> What, if, (as one ſpeaks) there were an <hi>even lay between the Negative and Affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mative?</hi> Would not <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> bid us ſtick to the <hi>ſafeſt ſide of the Queſtion;</hi> and make that <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> the Rule of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:65288:36"/>your Life? Inaſmuch, as, if no ſuch Day do come, <hi>Good Men</hi> muſt fare as well as <hi>Bad ones.</hi> But, if it doth come, they muſt fare as much better, as <hi>Rivers of Eternal Pleaſure,</hi> are more ſweet than a <hi>Lake of unquenchable Fire!</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſaid <hi>Euripides;</hi> and it was often repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Pyrrhon</hi> himſelf, <hi>Who knows but to Die is to Live?</hi> To return then;</p>
               <p>Religion, which is the <hi>only Salt,</hi> to ſeaſon and ſweeten this Life, is the <hi>only means</hi> to be thought of, for ſecuring the next.</p>
               <p>Phrenzy it ſelf cannot imagine, that Contempt of the Supream King, is the way to Preferment in his Court! Or, that, he who is <hi>only Wiſe,</hi> will ſet Crowns of Glory upon Fools? That he will make them happy for ever, who diſdain to ſeek his Acquaintance and Favour! And do as plainly love <hi>Earth, more than Heaven,</hi> as they love <hi>Heaven more than Hell!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Future Bleſſed State, is <hi>a Penny,</hi> which the Lord of it thinks too much for any, but <hi>Labourers in his Vineyard.</hi> Yea, Labourers to the Death therein. It is <hi>a Treaſure</hi> that he gives to none,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:65288:37"/>but ſuch as part with their <hi>Sins,</hi> and are diſpoſed to part with their <hi>Lives,</hi> for it. It is <hi>that Joy of his,</hi> which no one muſt have, but they who do faithfully improve his <hi>concredited Talents.</hi> It is <hi>that Feaſt,</hi> whereto none are admitted, but ſuch as have on them the <hi>Wedding-Garment, i. e.</hi> Imputed Righteouſneſs, Inherent, and Practical! It is <hi>that Prize,</hi> which none obtain, but they who <hi>accompliſh their Race.</hi> It is <hi>that Crown,</hi> which none muſt receive, but they who <hi>fight</hi> and <hi>conquer</hi> Fleſh, World, and Devil. It is <hi>that Houſe of the King,</hi> wherein no Man gets a Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but he who enters in at the <hi>Strait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate</hi> of Chriſtianity. It is that <hi>Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> which belongs to none, but to <hi>new-born</hi> Children, as well as <hi>Adopted</hi> ones. And to ſuch as not only <hi>are</hi> Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, but do <hi>walk</hi> as Children of the Moſt High! Wherefore, in every re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, <hi>Bleſſed are they who hear the Word of God and keep it!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ask you, now, ſeriouſly, <hi>What you ſhall do?</hi> Or, deriſorily, <hi>What it is that you can do?</hi> And, whether it be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed in what hath been ſaid, That
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:65288:37"/>
                  <hi>diſordered Clocks</hi> can ſet themſelves to rights? Or, <hi>dead Men</hi> recal their Lives? And, <hi>Men, whom Satan hath bound for many Years,</hi> can looſe, and let themſelves go?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sirs,</hi> You ſhall not be ſet about ought, that is either <hi>unneceſſary,</hi> or <hi>impoſſible.</hi> It is true; being corrupted in your no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt Parts, you can never reſtore your ſelves. In the Body, no Principles of Conſtitution can cure a Gangrene. And, in the Soul, when the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> and <hi>Will</hi> are vitiated, nothing of their own can reſtore their Rectitude. Becauſe, the <hi>Mind</hi> that ſhould direct, is more than Ignorant; even Erroneous. And, the <hi>Will</hi> that ſhould Command, is more than Impotent; even Malicious. Yea, and <hi>Sin,</hi> as deadly as it is, doth not <hi>ſmart,</hi> but <hi>ſtupify</hi> you; whereby your Vices, even the moſt cruel and ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary ones, be made like <hi>Soldiers Arms;</hi> not at all <hi>uneaſy,</hi> or any more <hi>a Burden</hi> to them than their very <hi>Limbs.</hi> And, more than that, they be even <hi>Ornaments</hi> in their Sight. Of that Mind was he, who ſaid concerning <hi>profane Swearing;</hi> That <hi>it was a pity that ſuch a good Grace
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:65288:38"/>of Speech ſhould be any Offence?</hi> In ſhort; if ever you are <hi>Saved,</hi> you muſt be <hi>new Created.</hi> And none but Almighty Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, can produce a <hi>New-Creature.</hi> Yet, know ye, <hi>Sirs,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God your Redeemer is before-hand with you. He giveth you more Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er <hi>to recover your ſelves, out of the Snare of the Devil,</hi> than you make uſe of. The Schools of <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Arminius,</hi> do agree in this, that ſo much Power is given unto every Man, as ſerves to <hi>ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify God's Commanding Man,</hi> and to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn Man's Diſobeying God;</hi> who as you know, promiſeth you, that <hi>the Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Hand ſhall make Rich.</hi> Yea, and he hath given you this abundant Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, to ſeek ſupernatural Grace; he hath ſaid it,
<q>The Meek he will teach his Way.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Meek</hi> are Men humble enough, to deſire the <hi>Favour to receive</hi> his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands; and the <hi>Grace to keep</hi> them. To deſire it, with congruous Grief and Shame of their Apoſtacy. And with entire Submiſſion to his Goſpel-way of Salvation; which is by <hi>Repentance, Faith, and new Obedience.</hi> Let it be
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:65288:38"/>told, if it be known, who did ever thus <hi>ſeek, and not find</hi> Eternal Life? Or, why ſhould it not be hoped, that the Mountains of your Spirits by this time are levelled? And that you are more than <hi>almoſt perſwaded</hi> to the Holy Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>If ſo; upon the Writer be the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, if you find it loſt Labour.</p>
               <p>To <hi>off with the Vipers which have faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned upon your Hands.</hi> The vain and vile Companions, whoſe Tongues are more venomous than Vipers Teeth. And whoſe choſen Company are under God's extream Curſe; <hi>A Companion of Fools ſhall be deſtroyed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To commence Friendſhips with Men of ſhining Faces.</hi> Holy Wiſdom makes the Face to ſhine. And, Wiſe Mens Aſſociates, have the reverſion of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom unto Salvation! <hi>He that walks with Wiſe Men ſhall be Wiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To take a Guide while you travel in</hi> Turky. This World, is <hi>Turky;</hi> a wild and ſtrange Countrey. And he who has opened you a way through it unto Heaven, he has appointed you <hi>Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial</hi> Guides to lead you therein. Guides,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:65288:39"/>guided themſelves by that Heavenly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible One; whoſe Conduct you may expect in your due uſe of them. Guides, of whom your Saviour hath ſaid, <hi>He that heareth them, heareth him; and he that deſpiſeth them, deſpiſeth him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To be very often upon bended Knees.</hi> To pray is to deſire, as Malefactors de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire their Pardon; and, as Lepers de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire their Cure. A ſhort-liv'd Vapor, cannot be ſuch a Prayer. But, what is ſincere and without ceaſing, it is never failing. It hath the promiſe of the King; and therefore is ſure to take the Kingdom of Heaven! <hi>Ask, and ye ſhall receive.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To take the Oath of Allegiance,</hi> i. e. Your Baptiſmal Covenant and Oath. Whereto, your thorow <hi>Conſent,</hi> and ſutable <hi>Walk,</hi> are all real Religion. The Lord have Mercy on the mad Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes; of which, ſome do place their Religion in no better than the very <hi>Spots</hi> and <hi>Blemiſhes</hi> of Religion. And others in no more, than the meer <hi>Faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> and <hi>Dreſs</hi> of it. Vain is their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, by whom this Oath is not taken; tho their Sect be ever ſo ſtrict. Be their
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:65288:39"/>Chriſtianity of this or that Form, <hi>Chriſt ſhall profit them nothing.</hi> Their Hearts be not <hi>cleanſed by the Inſpiration of the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> but deluded by ſome Angel of Light, or of Darkneſs. <hi>Baptiſm doth now ſave us; not the putting away of the filth of the Fleſh, but the anſwer of a good Conſcience towards God, by the Reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Finally, it ſhall not be loſt Labour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To keep your Hearts at your right Hands.</hi> To join <hi>Contemplation</hi> and <hi>Action,</hi> in all things of Religion. Not to <hi>conſider</hi> what you do, is moſt <hi>Inhumane;</hi> and not to <hi>perform</hi> the Duty you have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, is moſt <hi>Profane.</hi> It is an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean Creature, that either <hi>chews not the Cud;</hi> or, if it does, <hi>divideth not the Hoof.</hi> To act without Counſel, is to go upon four Feet. To conſult, and not to act, is to ſend your Brains a Woolgathering. <hi>Whatever your Hand finds to do, do it with all your Might!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Your <hi>Holy things,</hi> you muſt do, with Holy <hi>Thoughts</hi> and <hi>Pains.</hi> Strain the Nerves of your <hi>Mind,</hi> and of your <hi>whole Man.</hi> And, of all things, look you well to your <hi>Aims.</hi> Never go ye into
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:65288:40"/>
                  <hi>the Church,</hi> as Boys go into the <hi>Thames;</hi> not to waſh and cleanſe, but to divert themſelves. Hear Sacred things, ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to underſtand; make Religious Vows, reſolving to perform them; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring no longer to live than you do ſo!</p>
               <p>Look on <hi>Flatterers</hi> as ſo many <hi>Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers;</hi> turn you from them; and from your very ſelves, when you turn Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers to your ſelves. Be not the Apes of ſuch a Monſter as <hi>Vitellius,</hi> who upon the Approach of his Ruin, raiſed no other Fortification, but that of a <hi>drunken Mirth,</hi> which kept out the <hi>Noiſe</hi> and <hi>Report,</hi> but <hi>haſtned</hi> the Stroke of it. Remember, that <hi>wilful Sin,</hi> if any, muſt be your Death. Being that, neither <hi>God's Decrees,</hi> or <hi>Satan's Devices,</hi> do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit any rapes on your Souls. If you do not all that is here named, as many as are, themſelves, any wiſer, muſt <hi>pronounce you Wilful, and tremble at your haſtning Wo!</hi> Every Priſoner in Hell, cries out of his <hi>Will.</hi> Not complaining that his <hi>Judg</hi> was an <hi>hard Maſter,</hi> but his <hi>Heart</hi> was an <hi>hard Milſtone.</hi> Not able to ſay that he periſhed thrô <hi>meer Deceivable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> or otherwiſe than thrô his <hi>willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to be deceived!</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:65288:40"/>
               <p>And, may it not now be hoped, that your Minds are <hi>inlightned</hi> too much to be <hi>incenſed</hi> againſt this Advice? That your <hi>Enmity</hi> againſt your God is abated, and your <hi>Fear</hi> of him encreaſed? Juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or otherwiſe it is hoped ſo. And for the juſt and true Conqueſt of both your <hi>Fear and Enmity,</hi> you are preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with theſe Conſiderations.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The God to whom you are called is as merciful as can be deſired.</hi> For, he is In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely ſo.</p>
               <p>Indeed; our <hi>Miſery,</hi> and not our <hi>Sin,</hi> is the Object of his Mercy. <hi>Sin,</hi> is moſt contrary to his Government, yea, to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Godhead; and cannot but be the Ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ect of his vindictive Hatred. <hi>Pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um eſt Deicidium,</hi> Sch. Our <hi>Miſery,</hi> is the Object of his Mercy. Of the bleſſed Compaſſion, of which, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videth <hi>a new and living Way of Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> and, being provided, he is moſt ready to ſave the very chief of Sinners, <hi>turning into that way.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Inſomuch, that let us ſuppoſe any ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle one, to have committed all the Sins of <hi>Adam,</hi> and of his whole <hi>Progeny.</hi> The vaſt
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:65288:41"/>Ocean would not ſo eaſily and preſently quench one ſpark of Fire, as the Divine Mercy would forgive all thoſe Sins, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Sinner's believing on Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Blood of our Saviour is as Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory and Meritory, as can be deſired.</hi> For it is as the Holy Oracles name it, the <hi>Blood of God,</hi> i. e. of him, who is God equal with the Father, as well as Man, like unto his Brethren. And, this hath given more honour to God, than hath been taken from him by the Sins of Devils and Men. So that, without the leaſt loſs to his Glory, God may ſave the worſt Soul that <hi>Repents,</hi> and <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth on him</hi> that ſhed this Blood. And, in giving the Crown of Heavenly Glory, God giveth no more than his Son hath bought and paid for.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Power of the Holy Ghoſt to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert, and to comfort, is as great as can be deſired.</hi> For he is God equal with the Father and Son; and cannot but be Omnipotent. If we are Hells of Sin and of Sorrow; he can make us Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens of Purity and of Joy. Of Satan's
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:65288:41"/>Dunghils, he can make us God's Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. There be no Hearts, but what he can cleanſe by his Inſpirations.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Precedents and Examples of the moſt bloody Sinners ſaved, are as great as can be deſired.</hi> Sirs, as bad as your ſelves have been ſaved by the Mercy of the Father, by the Merits of the Son, and by the Power of the Holy Spirit. For, <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> a Monſter of Impiety and Villany, is now a Star in Glory. And, not a few of them who <hi>murdered our Redeemer on Earth,</hi> are now with him in Heaven. What a Catalogue have we 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9, 10, 11. <hi>Fornicators, Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, Adulterers, Effeminate, Abuſers of themſelves with Mankind, Thieves, Drunkards, Revilers, Extortioners.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Promiſes made to ſave other Rebels, are as great as can be deſired.</hi> For, there is not any one ſort of them to be named, but, upon their <hi>Repentance</hi> and <hi>Faith,</hi> have Salvation promiſed to them. Yea, as great Salvation, as any other. And, leſt any ſhould imagine themſelves to be excluded, moſt, if not all ſorts, are expreſly mentioned. Mentioned in the great and precious Offers and Promiſes
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:65288:42"/>of Salvation, upon their Converſion!</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The very Name of God is as ſweet and encouraging as can be deſired.</hi> The Name, expreſſing his good Affection towards the moſt hainous Sinners, when relent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and returning. For, it was this that was given his Servant <hi>Moſes,</hi> for the heartning of ſuch. <hi>Merciful, and Gracious, Longſuffering, and abundant in Goodneſs, and in Truth, keeping Mercy for thouſands, Forgiving (both) Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Tranſgreſſion, and Sin.</hi> A Name, one would think, ſufficient to drive De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair out of this World. And, confine it to Hell, its proper Seat.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Commands of God for the worſt of Sinners to hope, and to repent, are as great and as bright as can be deſired.</hi> None are more abſolute, none more expreſs. The words of a late <hi>excellent Author</hi> are Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beams.
<q>To preſcribe Repentance with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a foundation of Forgiveneſs, were inconſiſtent with God's Excellencies.</q> Nor is there any Cauſe why any Man under a call to Repentance, ſhould doubt of Forgiveneſs. Unleſs God be ready to forgive the Sins of Penitents, his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience is meerly ſubſervient to Wrath,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:65288:42"/>and a Reſolution to deſtroy. But, this would reflect unſpeakable Diſhonour on him. If a Man deal thus, it is a token of as evil a Mind as can be in him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Intreaties God ſendeth to the moſt lewd Sinners, to turn to him, are as kind as can be deſired.</hi> As ſignificative, I mean, of his aſtoniſhing Love, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of their Salvation upon his graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Terms. O bottomleſs Depth, and amazing Height of Divine Love! God <hi>beſeeches.</hi> God <hi>prays</hi> you to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled and ſaved. Soveraign Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, even <hi>courteth</hi> Worms. Infinite Mercy <hi>wooeth</hi> very Vipers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Parable in which God hath given the Picture of his Heart towards Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, is as moving as can be deſired.</hi> Luke 15. Review it; behold, a Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of yours, an horrid Prodigal, relents and humbles himſelf. And, what's the next News? His moſt merciful Father <hi>beholds</hi> him; <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionates</hi> him; <hi>runs</hi> toward him; <hi>falls on his Neck and kiſſes</hi> him; calls for the <hi>beſt Robe</hi> for him; for a <hi>Ring;</hi> for <hi>Shooes</hi> on his Feet; and for a <hi>Feaſt</hi> to be made.</p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:65288:43"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Wall of Fire God has made to keep you from your pernicious Follies, is as aweful as can be deſired.</hi> For, this Wall is Hell; and Hell is Torment of <hi>Extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity</hi> unto all <hi>Eternity.</hi> Wherewithal wo'd you then be held from your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive Courſes, if the Fear hereof will not curb your Luſts?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Kingdom God offers you, to draw you to his Love and Service, is as rich as can be deſired.</hi> For, it is high as Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, durable as Eternity, delightful as Joy in Extaſy! And, laſtly,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Admonition given you of all theſe Particulars, is as plain as can be deſired.</hi> That, which you have the refuſal of in the <hi>Sacred Oracles,</hi> is a very <hi>Light and Lamp.</hi> And, what you have in <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Writings,</hi> is not given in <hi>Clouds and Darkneſs.</hi> Both are ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you in ſuch a Light, that none of you can be <hi>blind,</hi> ſave only thoſe <hi>who will not ſee.</hi> Neither, can the moſt <hi>violent</hi> of you <hi>take Hell by any Force,</hi> without <hi>loving Darkneſs rather than Light!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sirs, your <hi>Lives</hi> are Vapours, your <hi>great Eſtates</hi> are great Snowballs. Thoſe
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:65288:43"/>are vaniſhing, theſe are melting. Your <hi>carnal Comforts,</hi> like your <hi>drunken ſerving-Men,</hi> will be out of the way, when you do moſt need them. For your <hi>rotten Sticks</hi> be not Fire, your <hi>Gloworms</hi> be not <hi>Stars;</hi> your <hi>ſhining Duſt</hi> is not <hi>Heaven.</hi> And your <hi>preſent excuſes of Sin,</hi> like other Thieves, at the approach of Light, will be ſure to be gone. Neither are your <hi>Breakfaſts</hi> of it, ſo full of Honey, as your Supper will be of Gall. Vanities, are very Changelings. <hi>Abſalom</hi>'s <hi>Hair,</hi> now is his <hi>Pride;</hi> but, anon it is his <hi>Halter. Jezabel</hi>'s <hi>Paint,</hi> makes her Face <hi>a heap of Charms</hi> for a while; but, 'tis not long before 'tis waſhed off with her Blood, and ſhe is trod under Foot. <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi>'s <hi>Robes</hi> are now <hi>reſplendent and Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al;</hi> but by and by they are <hi>over-run with Vermin,</hi> which eat up his miſerable Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty like Carrion; and make a ſad Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of his Sceleton. Sirs; ſay not that I roll in railing Rhetorick, and tumble in ugly Tropes. You do hate no <hi>Boanerges</hi> now, as you will hate your <hi>Paraſites</hi> one Day. The Day wherein <hi>the Root of your Merriments will be found
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:65288:44"/>to be Rotteneſs,</hi> and their <hi>Bloſſom ſhall riſe up as the Duſt.</hi> Wherefore, haſte, haſte, Gentlemen! The <hi>worſt of Men</hi> are willing to be <hi>Good,</hi> as <hi>Auſtin</hi> was to be Chaſte. And, <hi>the moſt of them</hi> do ſtay till they are in the Jaws of Hell, before they conſider what is the worth of a Soul. Wherefore, you are left with the words of the <hi>beſt Maſter,</hi> ſpoken to the <hi>worſt Servant;</hi> very kindly they are ſpoken to you;
<q>What you do, do quickly!</q>
               </p>
               <p>Then may it be ſaid to you that live in Proſperity, <hi>Peace be unto you, and Peace to your Houſes, and Peace unto all that you have;</hi> as <hi>David</hi>'s Youths were commanded to greet the Great Man of <hi>Maon,</hi> whoſe Poſſeſſions were in <hi>Carmel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Be doing therefore, good Sirs! and ſay not of your humble Monitor, as Cardinal <hi>Mattheo Langi,</hi> concerning <hi>Luther,</hi> viz. <hi>That thô the Romans needed a Scouring, it was not fit that they ſhould take it from ſo ſorry a Hand.</hi> Forgive me the Apoſtrophe, in which I leave you.</p>
               <p>So that our <hi>Worſhipful,</hi> our <hi>Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> and our <hi>Right Honourable</hi> Lepers,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:65288:44"/>may be cleanſed, and made wiſe to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Send O my Lord I pray thee, by the Hand of him whom thou wilt ſend!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Make no long tarrying, good Lord; but ſend ſome <hi>Eliphaz</hi> or other, with a more radiant Eloquence to tell them, that, <hi>They are deſtroyed from Morning to Morning! They periſh for ever with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any regarding it; their Excellency which is in them goeth away. They die even without Wiſdom.</hi> O ſend, before it be ſaid to this <hi>Gallant,</hi> and to that,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Fruits that thy Soul luſted after, are departed from thee; and all the things which were Dainty and Goodly, are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from thee; and thou ſhalt find them no more at all. In one hour thy great Riches are come to nought! Thy Soul is required of thee; and whoſe ſhall the things be which thou haſt provided?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>May ſuch as are deaf to a leſſer <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy,</hi> be made to hearken to a greater <hi>Paul</hi> or <hi>Peter!</hi> And they who have been as <hi>wicked,</hi> turn to be as <hi>wiſe,</hi> as that Son who ſaid to his Father, <hi>I will not! but afterward, he repented, and went.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:65288:45"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>To the Formal and Hypocritical.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE higheſt <hi>Elements</hi> are the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt; the topmoſt <hi>Boughs of Trees,</hi> bear the ſoundeſt Fruit; and the <hi>Hill-Countries</hi> have much the cleaneſt ways. But, <hi>Men of higheſt Degrees,</hi> be not ſo much of cleaneſt Morals. Great is their <hi>Britain,</hi> or painted Nation. He is, generally, but a <hi>Pict</hi> among them, who is not a very <hi>Saxon;</hi> not more than a <hi>Pretender</hi> to Religion, if any leſs than an <hi>open Enemy</hi> to it. To every ſuch Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tender God Almighty ſpeed this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter!</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gentlemen,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is not Apoſtolical to <hi>bite</hi> poor Mens Sores, and <hi>lick</hi> yours. Nor is it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible in your Caſe, to decline Lance and Cauſtick. What muſt profit you, is the <hi>Plainneſs</hi> which you name <hi>Rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi> the Liberty, which you deem to be Cruelty; the very Method, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Holy <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles</hi> hewed
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:65288:45"/>their Hypocrites. Not, <hi>ala-mode Talk;</hi> which as Pills lapped up in Pap and Sugar, have no bitter Reliſh, nor any ſweet Effect.</p>
               <p>You have therefore what follows. And, with the ſelf-ſame <hi>Accent,</hi> to your Worſhips of every Opinion, and Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Epiſc. Presb. Independ.</hi> &amp;c. It being no extraordinary Matter, with whom you run; whoſe Cry you follow; and whoſe <hi>Shibboleth</hi> you have taken to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce. For, without the true <hi>Scope</hi> and <hi>Subſtance</hi> of Religion, all external Formalities are equal Fooleries. And, their moſt punctual Obſervance is no wiſer than <hi>Domitian</hi>'s <hi>buſineſs,</hi> in catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Flies. Like the antient <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees,</hi> you may gliſter with your <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacteries and Tephilims.</hi> And reverence your ſelves, as highly as any Spaniſh <hi>Alumbrados or domeſtick Dreamers;</hi> but, Serpents be Serpents, thô their Skins be ever ſo richly painted. And, could Men perſwade themſelves that they were really <hi>Gods,</hi> their Conceit would make them but ſo <hi>much the worſe Men.</hi> Wherefore, know ye, Sirs, that,</p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:65288:46"/>
               <p>You have two Claſſes; one, of <hi>groſs,</hi> and another of <hi>cloſe</hi> Hypocrites. The <hi>Groſs,</hi> who are leſs <hi>blind,</hi> but more <hi>mad.</hi> Who do uſe Art and Fiction, to make their Mock Religion. Knowing, how far they are from the Holy <hi>State,</hi> and the <hi>Walk,</hi> which they counterfeit. As he, who upon the Stage acts the Part of a King, knows himſelf to be none. The <hi>cloſe</hi> Hypocrites, are you ſick of the Jaundies; to whom all things do ſeem golden, and rich. And, who do therefore think, as you ſpeak, when you call your ſelves Chriſtians; thô you neglect and hate God's Chriſt. Neglect his <hi>Grace,</hi> and hate his <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> and are no more his pardoned <hi>Favourites,</hi> or conſenting <hi>Subjects,</hi> than <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Tartars.</hi> But, are much black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Sinners than either; becauſe, you have Means; and you, if you would, might know both your Saviour and your ſelves.</p>
               <p>The things, which both of you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, is to be <hi>Children of God, and Heirs of Heaven.</hi> For, the leaſt of true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are no leſs. The Cloaks you do put on, are more and leſs fine. It con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:65288:46"/>not ſome <hi>Papiſts,</hi> to be <hi>common ones;</hi> but they muſt enter ſome <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Order.</hi> And, it will not ſerve all of you, to be <hi>common Proteſtants;</hi> ſome of you muſt be of this or that Sect. And <hi>Opinion, Party,</hi> and <hi>way of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> are your moſt cheap, but leaſt ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable, Cloak. Wherefore, ſome of you do go to the coſt of a <hi>demure Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance,</hi> and a <hi>reformed Life,</hi> and very <hi>many Works of Piety, Juſtice, and Charity!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Abundance of <hi>Snow</hi> is laid on, to make your Dunghils look like Gardens. Very many <hi>white Feathers</hi> are uſed to hide your black Skins. More than a few <hi>Flowers</hi> are procured to ſtrew your Corps. And to what end is this? To be <hi>Ceſar</hi>'s Friends, when <hi>Ceſar</hi> is God's Friend. But, moſtly, for fear of a Power ſuperior to any <hi>Ceſar.</hi> To e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape the <hi>flaming Sword of Conſcience;</hi> that is not to be averted without ſome <hi>Image of Holineſs.</hi> And ſometimes, to gratify the Concupiſcence of <hi>Vogue and Praiſe.</hi> Carnal ends, of your falſe Dealings, all of them. And, ſuch as are demonſtrative of a Mind, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in a carnal ſinful State! For, it's
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:65288:47"/>ſure, he loves <hi>a Dunghil,</hi> that adorns it; a <hi>Blackamore,</hi> that puts him in a fine Dreſs; and <hi>a Corps,</hi> that ſtrews Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers on it. It is moſt certain, when you go to charge in <hi>whitewaſhing</hi> and <hi>paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> an old rotten Houſe, you do not mean to <hi>pull it down.</hi> While you keep a ſtir to make you ſeem what you are not, you have no intention to make your ſelves what you ought to be! And, what you muſt become, or it had been better you had never been born. <hi>For the Name of Religion</hi> which you get without any <hi>Merit,</hi> you hold without any <hi>Profit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, by what Witchcraft are you held from all manner of Thought? Or, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this, do you ſometimes think hereof? <hi>Sc.</hi> How you ſhould take it, if your Servants did ſet upon your Tables no more than the <hi>Hair</hi> of your Oxen; the <hi>Feathers</hi> of your Fowls; the <hi>Shells</hi> of your Fiſh? Giving the beſt of all three, to your ſworn Enemies. No better do you <hi>ſerve,</hi> and no leſs do you <hi>mock</hi> your great Maſter! Putting him off with no more than <hi>falſe ſhews</hi> of Honour, Love, and Worſhip. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:65288:47"/>the Eſtimation of your Minds, the Affection of your Hearts, and the Obedience of your Lives, upon your Idols! This is your dealing with <hi>I AM THAT I AM.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Heathen World</hi> was not ſo blind, but it ſaw this; <hi>God being a Spirit,</hi> is to be worſhip'd in Spirit. The Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monious <hi>Jewiſh one</hi> was taught, that the <hi>true Circumciſion was that of the Heart.</hi> And, ſhall any of the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an World</hi> doubt it? Thus ſpeaks the Goſpel Covenant; <hi>I will write my Law in their Heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Deceive not your ſelves with Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits, that all is well, and you have the inward parts, as well as the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ones of Chriſtianity. You know, that <hi>a dead Man hath inward Parts.</hi> But, what then? He hath them <hi>dead;</hi> and ſo, hath no <hi>inward Man.</hi> You have likewiſe many rare Parts in you; but the Miſery is, they are dead. In ſhort, it is a <hi>dead Body</hi> wherein the Soul lives not. And a <hi>dead Soul</hi> it is, wherein the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> lives not. That Holy work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Grace, with all the Graces which are his Holy Works. Dead you are
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:65288:48"/>
                  <hi>if you dwell not in God, and God in you!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Until you love God, and nothing elſe, but for God's ſake; it is but in <hi>degree,</hi> that you differ from <hi>the worſt of Men.</hi> So as <hi>Toads</hi> do differ from <hi>Aſps.</hi> But, it is in <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Kind</hi> that Men truly Good do excel you. So as <hi>Wheat</hi> excels <hi>Chaff,</hi> and <hi>Children</hi> excel <hi>Dogs.</hi> And plainly it muſt be ſaid. <hi>The Lord hath not yet given you an Heart to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, and Eyes to ſee, and Ears to hear!</hi> To <hi>hear</hi> his Word and <hi>do it.</hi> The <hi>Son of Perdition,</hi> was firſt a <hi>cloſe Diſſembler,</hi> and afterwards a <hi>bold Traitor.</hi> Not afraid to go ſtraitway from the <hi>Holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to the Execution of <hi>the moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed Project.</hi> There is a juſt Fear of many of your ſelves. Will it pleaſe you therefore to obſerve particularly?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There is a ſpecious Repentance, in which you may periſh. Judas,</hi> periſhed in his. He had a <hi>deadly</hi> Sorrow for Sin, but no <hi>godly</hi> one. And ſo may you. You do grieve for your Sin! And ſo does every Felon, when he comes to <hi>Tyburn.</hi> You do turn, <hi>and caſt away your Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions!</hi> And, ſo do <hi>Seamen</hi> caſt their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Goods to the Sea's bottom, in a
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:65288:48"/>Storm. Yet they venture their Lives, to get them up again, in a Calm. Know it, Sirs; as <hi>there is a trembling of Heart which is a true ſaving Grace; there is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, a trembling of Heart, which Divines, as well as Phyſicians, do call a dangerous Diſeaſe.</hi> Pejus poenituit quam peccavit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>das, ſaith St. <hi>Auſtin. You repent not unto Life,</hi> if you count not, that, to diſhonour God is worſe than Death. And, if you break not off your Sins, as a <hi>Priſoner</hi> doth his Irons; with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire they may never come on any more.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There is a Senſe, in which you may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and be damned. Devils</hi> do believe and tremble. And what are your Thoughts of <hi>Simon Magus?</hi> You may believe the Goſpel as a <hi>Hiſtory;</hi> ſo you do the Gazette. And who queſtions, but the <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of it is believed alſo by <hi>Beelzebub?</hi> Your Faith is vain, and you are dead in your Sin, if you do not <hi>rely</hi> on it, as it is a <hi>Promiſe</hi> of Grace; and do not <hi>conform</hi> to it, as it is <hi>a Rule of Life!</hi> The Faith is damning, which, like <hi>Rachel,</hi> thô it be beautiful, is bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren!</p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:65288:49"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>There is a Worſhip, of which you may give God much, and not honour him at all. Ephraim</hi> and <hi>Judah,</hi> gave him that, which he named <hi>Lies and Deceit.</hi> You do verbally confeſs Sins! But, is it not without lamenting them? You ask for Grace! But, it is poſſible you may not be in much Pain till you have it. You <hi>ſpeak</hi> God's Praiſe! But ſo you may do, and <hi>give</hi> him none; for, what the Heart does not, it is all undone. Hecatombs without Hearts, are the Sacrifice of Fools.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There are rare Gifts, which you' may have; and uſe to the Profit of others; and yet periſh your ſelves. The Son of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,</hi> had others Gifts beſide the Bag. And, for Idleneſs he was never taxed, that we read. <hi>Spiders,</hi> the Naturaliſts ſay, have <hi>eight Eyes.</hi> Have you <hi>Eyes that are clear?</hi> So hath many a <hi>veno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Creature.</hi> Do you excite others to do good? So do <hi>Drums and Trumpets,</hi> which abide ſenſeleſs themſelves. <hi>Swenk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field,</hi> had no ſmall gift of Prayer; and was a great Alms-giver; yet he was a Monſter.</p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:65288:49"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>There are very religious Affections, which you may have, and yet be dead in Sins.</hi> John Baptiſt<hi>'s Diſciples</hi> for a Seaſon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joiced in his Light. Do your Lamps burn? So did the <hi>fooliſh Virgins</hi> for a time. Do you ſometimes ſhed Tears at a Sermon? So have ſome that lived the while in Fornication. It is no new thing, for Mens Hearts to thaw in the Sun, and freeze in the Shade. One day to <hi>ſigh</hi> and <hi>groan</hi> in the Congregation, and the next to <hi>rant</hi> and <hi>roar</hi> in the Tavern!</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There is a Love of the Saints, which you may have and be none your ſelves. The Heathens,</hi> which ſhewed St. <hi>Paul</hi> no ſmall kindneſs, were not Saints. You love them becauſe they love you! <hi>But do not even the Publicans ſo?</hi> You love them for ſome or other Gift of theirs, which charmeth you. But, do not you ſo love your <hi>Hounds</hi> and <hi>Hawks?</hi> You are of the World which hates the Saints, if you love them not, becauſe <hi>they love God and are beloved of God.</hi> And, if you command not your ſelves, even then to love them, when you contradict your <hi>doubtful Opinions,</hi> and tell you of
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:65288:50"/>your <hi>unqueſtionable</hi> Sins. There be Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions of ſtrange Spirits, that <hi>love not the King,</hi> and yet <hi>laviſh away Money on his Servants.</hi> That ſay of God's Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice <hi>what a wearineſs is it.</hi> Yet will ſay to a Servant of his, as <hi>Herod</hi> to the Damſel, <hi>Whatſoever thou ſhalt ask I will give thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There is a lovely Sincerity, which you may have, and yet be damned for Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſy. Saul,</hi> had a natural and laudable one, before his Converſion; and while the Wrath of God abode upon him. You have true and honeſt Hearts, as to many moral Acts! And had not <hi>Abimelech</hi> as honeſt an one as you? <hi>Julian</hi> the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate was of a Converſation very ſtrict; and it appears not but, that, of a long time, be <hi>thought</hi> as bad as he <hi>ſpake!</hi> All <hi>Sincerity</hi> is not <hi>godly.</hi> There is a <hi>wild Olive</hi> of it, as well as <hi>a true.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There is an unbroken Quietneſs, which you may have, without any true Peace. Dives,</hi> had juſt ſuch; his Prologue ſpeaks Quietneſs; <hi>Soul take thine Eaſe!</hi> But, God's Epilogue ſpeaks a diſtance from Peace; <hi>Thou Fool this Night thy Soul ſhall be taken againſt thy Will</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:65288:50"/>
                  <hi>eſt poſcere à Notente. Caſaub.</hi>) You have no Sin, that troubles you! It may be ſo. You name your Sleep in Sin a ſweet <hi>Reſt!</hi> No doubt but it ſeems ſo. And, you do think it a good <hi>Bleſſing of God's ſending!</hi> Moſt Dreamers do dream ſo. But verily, Sirs, if God ſends ſuch a Reſt and Quietneſs, he ſends it as he ſends Sword and Peſtilence! He ſends it in Wrath, and for Vengeance. For never is he ſo angry with a Man, as when he ſaith, <hi>Let him alone!</hi> And when he asks, <hi>Wherefore ſhould he be ſtricken any more?</hi> Wherefore,</p>
               <p>Is there not a Cauſe, think ye, for this Advice? That either you turn <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> or throw away your <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Names! Naomi,</hi> being ſunk into a Condition that was contrary, threw off hers; <hi>Call me no more</hi> Naomi, <hi>but</hi> Marah. Why ſhould <hi>Goats</hi> be called <hi>Sheep,</hi> thô found in their Skins? Skins which very <hi>Wolves</hi> may put on, and often do ſo, for a Seaſon. Do not wilfully continue dead, if you obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately <hi>deſire a Name to live.</hi> Come then quite out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> if you muſt needs think your ſelves in <hi>Canaan.</hi> The
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:65288:51"/>
                  <hi>Devil</hi> ſpeaks as kindly as <hi>Pharaoh, I will let you go, only you ſhall not go far,</hi> Exod. 8.28. <hi>Fleſh, World,</hi> and <hi>Devil,</hi> do brook all but <hi>thorow Religion.</hi> Go therefore, go.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pray that you may receive your Sight!</hi> You know nothing yet, but the <hi>Words</hi> and the <hi>Geſtures</hi> of Religion; the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> the <hi>Truth,</hi> and the <hi>Goodneſs</hi> of it, your Eyes behold not. <hi>Nicodemus</hi> knows nothing of Regeneration.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Learn what is the Sinful, and what is the Holy State;</hi> There is no third; eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man is in one of the two. Every Man is a <hi>Saint, and hath the Holy Spirit;</hi> or he is a <hi>Samaritan, and hath a Devil.</hi> The Sinful State is that, wherein a Man hates, and is hated of God. The Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly State is that, wherein God and Man are reconciled. A Man loves God, and is loved of him. In the firſt, God and Man are oppoſed as Fire and Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; In the ſecond, God and Man are endeared as Father and Son! Make your <hi>Judgment</hi> then, and your <hi>Choice!</hi> In order whereto,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Believe the Fountain of Truth, againſt the Father of Lies.</hi> Conclude, the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:65288:51"/>Scriptures to be true, every word. And be aſſured of all they ſay, as of the things which you ſee with your Eyes. <hi>Value</hi> them, <hi>read, follow,</hi> and <hi>prefer</hi> them, above the Light of the Sun!</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Act the parts of Men, in your endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to be Saints.</hi> Uſe your <hi>Reaſon,</hi> in your purſuits of <hi>Religion.</hi> God, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livens Men by <hi>awakening</hi> their Reaſon. Satan, murders them by holding it in <hi>Sleep.</hi> What is your Sin, indeed, but <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonableneſs?</hi> Want of Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is moſt, or all Mens Damnation. It can never be well with you, till <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> corrects the errors of <hi>Senſe;</hi> and <hi>Faith</hi> corrects the errors of <hi>Reaſon.</hi> For <hi>Reaſon</hi> is but <hi>a Rule, by the Word and Spirit ruled.</hi> Yet as ſoon will God give you to ſee with your Eyes ſhut, as to judg with your Reaſon un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exerciſed. Indeed, <hi>crack'd Heads be Sockets for new Lights;</hi> but it's becauſe all ſuch be falſe ones.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſolve that the Concerns of Eternity, ſhall have the beſt of your Time.</hi> That no Mills of ſecular Buſineſs, or Circles of ſenſual Pleaſure, ſhall have your <hi>beſt</hi> Hours; or your <hi>deepeſt</hi> Thoughts.
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:65288:52"/>No, but, the Morning, (that is the <hi>Graces</hi> Friend as well as <hi>the Muſes</hi>) ſhall always be taken up in Sacred Buſineſs. And, of other Seaſons, <hi>All the Fat ſhall be the Lord's;</hi> He hath <hi>but one Day in ſeven;</hi> let him not have leſs than <hi>one Hour in ſeven,</hi> every Day.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Take faſt hold of faithful Reprovers.</hi> Are there none near you? Send for them, as <hi>Cornelius</hi> for <hi>Peter.</hi> And, when you have them, let them not go! Keep them, as more needful to your Souls, than <hi>Butlers</hi> and <hi>Cooks</hi> for your Bodies. Turn them not away for cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Fire, Fire,</hi> when you and yours are <hi>nigh unto burning.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Beware of the Phrenzy of the Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Beggar.</hi> Who could not be perſwad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but all the Ships in the Harbour were his. <hi>Tormenting Fears</hi> do not half the hurt of <hi>preſumptuous Hopes.</hi> Who will have his Arm taken from his Shoulderblade, unleſs he believe it to be gangreen'd? Or, who of you will <hi>run that he may obtain,</hi> if he preſumes himſelf to have ran and obtained al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready? Deceitful Hopes avert from all <hi>endeavours,</hi> and the very <hi>deſires</hi> that be requiſite to Salvation.</p>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:65288:52"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Often compare the Gain of Godlineſs, and the Profit of Sin.</hi> The <hi>Natures,</hi> the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes,</hi> the <hi>Durations,</hi> of the one and the other. Draw up a Catalogue, or Inventory of them; Or read them of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in Authors, that have drawn them up to your Hand. And, then,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Night and Day conſider the Danger of Delays.</hi> Tell your ſelves, that, a <hi>fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Repentance,</hi> is not a Preparation for the <hi>Judgment to come.</hi> And, that, it is no <hi>Repentance</hi> at all, which is not <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire</hi> without Reſerve, and <hi>preſent</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Delay. God's voice, to every Man of you, is this; <hi>Ariſe, leſt thou be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed. Eſcape for thy Life; look not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind thee!</hi> Haſte therefore, and,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Do the Act which is the moſt momentous one of your Life!</hi> The act, before which, <hi>the Wrath of God abideth on you!</hi> And, after which, <hi>there is no Condemnation to you!</hi> With Judgment, Sincerity, and Gratitude, give your ſelves to God in Chriſt! Join your ſelves in Covenant unto the Father, Son, and Spirit! For, there is no other God in Heaven, but the Triune! And, the <hi>Socinian</hi> is but a more ſubtle ſort of <hi>Mahometan.</hi> Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:65288:53"/>Dr. <hi>Pocock</hi> obſerved, that our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our was more honoured in <hi>Turky</hi> than in <hi>Cracovia!</hi> In ſhort; Mr. <hi>Howe</hi>'s <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimo</hi> of Self-Reſignation, is a Diamond. And, ſo is Bleſſed <hi>Allein</hi>'s Manual of Converſion?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Being made God's Temples, keep Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters at your Doors.</hi> You do no ſooner join unto the Lord in the Goſpel-Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, but you become <hi>Sacred Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> of the Holy Ghoſt. And, becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch, it concerns you to ſet a ſtrict Watch. That no <hi>unclean</hi> thing enter you. That, Things and Perſons, and whatever is <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nholy,</hi> be put out of your Society! For, <hi>If any defile the Temple of God, him will God deſtroy.</hi> But,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Think it not enough to abſtain from Sin.</hi> You do not think it enough for your Servants, to forbear <hi>ſmiting</hi> you, without <hi>ſerving</hi> you. And, what, if, from this Hour, you never ſinned any more? <hi>Stocks, and Stones, do not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit any Sins.</hi> So very <hi>poor a Praiſe</hi> it is to <hi>die unto Sin,</hi> if you <hi>live not unto God!</hi> Would you appear the Children of God? You muſt <hi>abound in the Work of the Lord.</hi> And, be <hi>holy,</hi> as well as <hi>harmleſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:65288:53"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Look not for the Aids which God hath promiſed, without the uſe of all Means which he hath required.</hi> He hath ſaid, he will give Wiſdom, and Will, and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, to do good. But, not, unleſs you <hi>ask.</hi> He hath not ſaid, you ſhall <hi>find</hi> unleſs you <hi>ſeek.</hi> Yea, <hi>ſeek with the whole Heart.</hi> And, <hi>Watch daily at Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom's Gates, and wait at the Poſts of its Doors! God had given his Apoſtle all that ſailed with him; Yet, without ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, he pronounced, that, Except they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode in the Ship, they could not be ſaved!</hi> Acts 27.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aim as high as Perfection.</hi> No <hi>ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual</hi> Man, covets leſs than perfect <hi>Health,</hi> and <hi>Strength,</hi> and <hi>Beauty.</hi> Nor does any <hi>ſpiritual</hi> one, crave leſs than per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <hi>Knowledg, Love,</hi> and <hi>Obedience.</hi> He is not Holy enough to be admitted into Heaven, who deſires no more than needs for his Admiſſion. <hi>Solomon</hi> calls it <hi>deſpiſing of a Man's Soul,</hi> to be content with low Attainments for it. And, to be ſtingy, and pinching, and ſparing of Pains to accompliſh it. Sincere Love of God aſpires to <hi>fulfilling</hi> of the Law of God! It's the <hi>Bond of Perfectneſs;</hi>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:65288:54"/>and that which holds all our Faculties, and Powers in the purſuit of it. In Religion, he that deſigns but a Medio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crity, is under the reigning power of Hypocriſy. A true Chriſtian thinks not himſelf a <hi>ſufficiently good Man,</hi> till he is as <hi>holy as the beſt Angel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whatever you are doing, remember you are dying.</hi> Lamps are <hi>waſting</hi> as ſoon as they burn; and we are <hi>dying,</hi> as ſoon as we live. How often, in the Womb, is Life ſpent before Breath is drawn? It's ſure, <hi>we are on our way</hi> toward ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World, before we are <hi>born into this,</hi> and as long as we <hi>breath in it.</hi> It is dying that we live. And, there's no <hi>Dweller</hi> on the Earth, but what is a <hi>Paſſenger.</hi> As in a Ship under Sail, whatever Men are doing, they are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly and ſwiftly paſſing. It is Dying, that you eat, drink, and ſleep; Dying that you buy, ſell, or game; Dying, that you read, hear, or pray. And it is a great need that you have of Death in your Thoughts, to quicken <hi>you</hi> to care of your Ways. Dr. <hi>Bates</hi> his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of the four laſt Things, was ate, and drank by <hi>the beſt of Queens.</hi> Happy
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:65288:54"/>
                  <hi>England,</hi> when our <hi>Nobility,</hi> and <hi>Gentry</hi> entertain themſelves as wiſely!</p>
               <p>But alas! <hi>Titius</hi> is in danger of the Sea breaking in upon all that he hath. With much coſt he builds <hi>a Wall</hi> to keep it out. Only, he leaves a <hi>huge Gap</hi> in his Wall. Yet, <hi>many ſee the Wall, who ſee not the Gap;</hi> and therefore do <hi>admire the Work, and praiſe the Man.</hi> But <hi>Sempronius,</hi> a leſs negligent, and more skilful Obſerver, ſpies the Gap. And, is ſick to ſee the <hi>abſurdity of the Wall,</hi> and the <hi>Folly of</hi> Titius. Predicting his Ruin, unleſs the Gap be ſtopp'd with Expedition!</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lords and Gentlemen,</hi> the Caſe is your own! There be vaſt Gaps in the Walls of your moſt operous and ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Religion. And, theſe you are called to have effectually ſtopp'd! Ask not, any of you, (for you are already told) <hi>What is your Treſpaſs, and what is your Sin, that you are ſo hotly purſued? Elijahs</hi> muſt tell <hi>Ahabs,</hi> that <hi>they and their Fathers Houſes have troubled</hi> Iſrael; <hi>in that they have forſaken the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Lord, and have followed</hi> Baalam. And, if a very <hi>David</hi> ſhall
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:65288:55"/>cloak his Sin, <hi>Nathan</hi> muſt ſay plainly, <hi>Thou art the Man.</hi> Wherefore, be it your care, that, you be not driven one Day to ſay; <hi>We are very guilty concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our plain Monitor; in that we ſaw the anguiſh of his Soul, when he beſought us to ſtop our Gaps, and we would not hear him. Therefore is diſtreſs come upon us!</hi> In hope of preventing it, I have follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Counſel to his Sons, <hi>Gen.</hi> 43. I have taken of the Fruit <hi>of Canaan,</hi> and brought you this Preſent; <hi>A little Balm, a little Honey, Spices, and Myrrh, Nuts and Almonds.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>To the truly Religious.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>GOodneſs and Greatneſs are a rare Conjunction. What more Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, than <hi>le Bon &amp; le Grand!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Holy <hi>Wiſdom</hi> tho it be, it ſelf, the greateſt, is <hi>good with an Inheritance.</hi> q. d. As good as it is, it is not always good that it ſhould be alone. Riches are an <hi>help meet for it.</hi> And,</p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:65288:55"/>
               <p>When joined together, they do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably ſerve each other. They eminent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſimilate their Profeſſor unto their Creator. They aſſimlate unto him, in <hi>being good, and doing it.</hi> In the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Attributes of <hi>Bleſſedneſs</hi> and <hi>Benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neither doth the King of Kings, wholly deny us ſuch Repreſentatives of his. To ſome few of you he gives the Honour to be ſuch. Making you as viſibly rich in <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>good Works,</hi> as in <hi>Money</hi> and <hi>Lands.</hi> Encreaſed with the Goods of both Worlds; the <hi>Volatile</hi> ones of this Earth, and the <hi>more endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Subſtance</hi> of Heaven. And, as for ſuch of you,</p>
               <p>All Men acknowledg your Order to be moſt <hi>Noble.</hi> Preciſeneſs it ſelf ſtiles you <hi>Right Honourable.</hi> Becauſe being ſo exalted by God, you exalt not your ſelves but him. You are <hi>wiſe</hi> and <hi>juſt;</hi> and, being <hi>inſtructed,</hi> you wax wiſer. Being <hi>reproved,</hi> you love your Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver! And,</p>
               <p>It is here concluded, your Honours will not think ſcorn to be <hi>catechiſed.</hi> Or, asked, in general, Firſt;</p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:65288:56"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Are there not with you, even with you, Sins againſt the Lord your God? Galileo</hi>'s Glaſſes do ſhow Spots in the Sun. Spots, ſome ſay, as big as <hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Africa.</hi> But, do not unaſſiſted Eyes ſpy your Faults? And, with your <hi>Gnats,</hi> very <hi>Camels;</hi> with <hi>Motes,</hi> very <hi>Beams?</hi> Have you no need, think you, of Snuffers to your Lamps? And daily remembrancers of your ſpiritual Diſtempers? Are the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Oils of wholſome Reproof, the leaſt of your Wants? Sirs,</p>
               <p>With your leave ſuppoſed, it is asked alſo, particularly,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Do you indeed, <hi>marry in the Lord!</hi> In the Lord, and by his Law, do you match your ſelves, and your Sons and Daughters? Is Divine Counſel, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſeriouſly asked? Is <hi>Religion,</hi> any of the <hi>Marriage-Articles</hi> you agree up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Or, if any, is it not the firſt that is laſt ſerved? <hi>Protenùs ad Cenſum, de Moribus ultima fiet Qeſtio.</hi> May it not be ſaid of many a one, as of <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram; He walked in the way of the Kings of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>for the Daughter of</hi> Ahab <hi>was his Wife?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:65288:56"/>2. <hi>Do you train up your Children in the way</hi> of Salvation? Have you, your ſelves, much ſpeech with them about their Souls? And, are you much more curious in the choice of their <hi>Tutors,</hi> than of your <hi>Huntſmen and Falconers?</hi> Do you go to the coſt of <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> for your <hi>Alexanders?</hi> As <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> are you content with nothing but an <hi>Arſenius?</hi> A Man, in whom Learning and Vertue ſtrive for Preheminence. <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> may I ſay what I have known? More than a few of your Children, are <hi>ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at Nurſe</hi> by dry Breaſts. And ſome are <hi>poiſoned at Nurſe,</hi> by the cancer'd Breaſts of vicious Teachers. A mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous thing! that your <hi>Minds</hi> and <hi>Hearts</hi> ſhould endure a Teacher, who either hath not a <hi>cloven Tongue,</hi> or hath a <hi>cloven Foot.</hi> One, who is not either a <hi>Learned Saint,</hi> or a moſt <hi>accompliſhed Hypocrite.</hi> That, ſuch as you ſhould commit <hi>your Jewels,</hi> into any but <hi>rare Hands</hi> to poliſh them. Particularly,</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Do you teach your Children early, the danger of Proſperity?</hi> Their danger of periſhing, upon the <hi>golden Sands.</hi> Which is not leſs, than their poor
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:65288:57"/>Neighbours periſhing in the <hi>deeps</hi> of Poverty. Do you ſhew them <hi>the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Captive with her Head ſhaved?</hi> The bewitching World, with the Vanity of its Glories diſcovered. Do you tell them, and prove to them by Experiments, what <hi>Shadows</hi> all its <hi>Juno</hi>'s are? Nay, do you not, ever and anon, let fall Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions which do <hi>poiſon their Minds?</hi> And, add to their innate Idolatry of <hi>Wealth,</hi> and <hi>Honour,</hi> and <hi>Pleaſure?</hi> Bethink your ſelves, and anſwer; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you do not give them occaſion to launce you, as <hi>a Noble Man</hi> of this Kingdom, was once launced by a young <hi>Nephew</hi> of his.</p>
               <p>Being <hi>Guardian</hi> to the ſaid <hi>Nephew,</hi> he made him ſick of waiting upon his Lordſhip's Vanities; and deſirous of croſſing the Seas, for a Writ of Eaſe from that attendance. Yet, at parting, his firſt charge was, <hi>That the young Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman ſhould by no means change his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi> Aſtoniſhed at this, the <hi>Nephew</hi> forthwith replies, <hi>Fear not that, my Lord; for as you have bred me, no Body will change with me.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:65288:57"/>
               <p>The <hi>Jews in Barbary,</hi> we are told, do every Morning give their Children Honey or Sugar; ſaying, <hi>as this is ſweet to thy Taſte, let Learning be ſweet to thy Heart.</hi> What effects might we ſee, if Chriſtians would, with like conſtancy, inſtil Inſtructions into their Youth? And, eſpecially as to the Objects of their higheſt <hi>Eſteem</hi> and <hi>Delight.</hi> By Error wherein, is their perpetual Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For, be it conſidered,</p>
               <p>This is a ſure Rule. <hi>They neither ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour or love God as God, who do not love and honour him above all Creatures.</hi> No thing is weight, which doth not draw the Scale. That which makes one <hi>Scale</hi> weigh down the other, makes the <hi>Weight.</hi> Our Honour and Love of God, are light, <hi>and far from Weight,</hi> until they do <hi>preponderate.</hi> Nor are they to be reckoned Love and Honour, when they do not weigh down all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Becauſe, then, ſome <hi>baſe Idol</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries down the Scale, and is of more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count than the <hi>Triune God.</hi> In ſhort; <hi>Homage</hi> is to be reckoned by <hi>Surpluſſage:</hi> and <hi>our Love of the moſt High,</hi> never <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſts,</hi> until it <hi>exceeds;</hi> never <hi>begins,</hi> till it
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:65288:58"/>
                  <hi>tranſcends.</hi> The many who <hi>reckon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe</hi> ſhall be made to <hi>reckon again,</hi> at the grand Audit.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Do you chooſe God's Servants</hi> to <hi>ſerve you?</hi> Do you not ever take Servants, without asking whether they do or will ſerve God? And do you not keep them without enquiring, what uſe they make of their <hi>holy Baptiſm?</hi> Is it any thing to you, whether they who wait at your Tables, do ever come to the Lord's Table, or no? Sirs, your Father <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Servants were taught and commanded; and ſo ſhould his Childrens Servants be!</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Do you eſteem highly Chriſt's Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry?</hi> And, that for their work ſake? Do you not frown any of them into Silence and Sadneſs? Do you not tempt them to give you your Character like <hi>Antigonus</hi> his Picture, which was half faced, that the deformity might be concealed? Do you glad them by asking their Advice? Saying to one and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as the ſick Child's Father to the Biſhop of Souls; <hi>If thou canſt do any thing, come help us!</hi> Do you tell them, as <hi>Alexander</hi> told a Flatterer of his; If
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:65288:58"/>thou ſeeſt not my Faults, thou art not a <hi>Philoſopher:</hi> if thou doſt ſee them and not admoniſh me, thou art a <hi>Traitor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By the way, it muſt be asked; do you never take into your Chappel, <hi>Salt that is fitter for the Dunghil?</hi> Do you never make a <hi>Judas,</hi> your Apoſtle to a Benefice? Do you never put <hi>a ſtinking Snuff</hi> into a golden Candleſtick? Do you never ſend a <hi>blind Man,</hi> to be the Guide of a Pariſh? And a <hi>Blackmore</hi> to whiten all the Souls of it?</p>
               <p>Beſides, it may be asked; whether you are not ſometimes ſick of the beſt of <hi>Heaven's Ambaſſadors?</hi> Reckoning them as ſo many <hi>Bills of Charges</hi> on you. Even while you keep at diſtance ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent from the <hi>Macedonian</hi> Fault. That, of <hi>giving beyond your Power.</hi> Have you not made ſome of them <hi>as poor as</hi> Job, for their imitating St. <hi>Paul?</hi> For their diſuſe of the <hi>enticing words of Man's Wiſdom;</hi> for their condeſcending to your Capacities; and not preaching in the Clouds? Do you not oftimes, <hi>deſpiſe their Propheſyings?</hi> Staying from a <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> to play a <hi>Game.</hi> Being much leſs <hi>ſwift to hear,</hi> than to excuſe the Sin of
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:65288:59"/>not Hearing. And, ſevenfold leſs at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentive to the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> than your Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours are to the <hi>Stage.</hi> Time runs too faſt they think at a <hi>Play-houſe;</hi> as long as Wit can run, they wiſh the Sun wouldſt and ſtill. But, at a <hi>Sermon,</hi> do not you watch the Glaſs, with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Luſt? In a word; Have you not a practice of <hi>robbing the Miniſters, which are higheſt in your Favours?</hi> Your Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains eſpecially? Calling them to you, and detaining them with you; with an unmerciful Frequence, and a moſt tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Impriſonment, waſting your Hours (as oft as your Levity can call forth theirs) in Squibs and Jeſts. Without a mu or gru of religious Conference; without a word <hi>ſeaſoned with Salt.</hi> This is <hi>Theft,</hi> and <hi>Sacrilege,</hi> for <hi>you devour that which is Holy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is poſſible, that, in ſuch days as ours, you may take a pride in <hi>keeping Chaplains.</hi> So rare a thing it is grown, that you may riſe up to <hi>Micah</hi>'s pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption; <hi>Now I know that the Lord will do me good, ſeeing I have a</hi> Levite <hi>to be my Prieſt.</hi> But, you are wiſer when you are your ſelves; if, as it is
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:65288:59"/>ſuppoſed, you are <hi>Iſraelites indeed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. Do you <hi>make the excellent of the Earth all your Delight?</hi> Are you nice in the Choice of Friends and Aſſociates? Do you mind how much your Welfare in Time and to Eternity, depends up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your Company? Upon your <hi>choice,</hi> and your <hi>uſe</hi> of Company? Do you ſhut out Lepers? Do you put to cure Men that are not hopeleſs? And, into your Boſoms, do you take none, but ſuch as are of ſerious Religion? The <hi>Fowls</hi> of the Air, and the <hi>Beaſts</hi> of the Field, keep not <hi>Heterogeneous</hi> Company. All the <hi>Herd,</hi> do caſt out the <hi>Deer that is cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and wounded.</hi> And <hi>all the Flocks of a Feather,</hi> do excommunicate ſuch as are of <hi>any other.</hi> They are leſs wiſe, to whom it is all one, whether their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorts be <hi>Saints</hi> or <hi>Brutes.</hi> And, who do forget what every Body knows, that if a <hi>Joſeph</hi> fall among Courtiers, he will rap out Oaths. If the High Prieſt's Hall do take a <hi>Peter,</hi> it turns him into a <hi>Judas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. Do you <hi>haſten to get reconciled, to any whom you have wronged?</hi> To any, tho ever ſo poor a Body. Do you not
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:65288:60"/>conceit, that it is a ſmall matter for a <hi>Cedar</hi> to wrong a <hi>Shrub?</hi> For, the <hi>Fat of the Earth</hi> to bite the <hi>Lean?</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Mr. <hi>Boyl,</hi> would ask forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Servants, if he had let fall any rebuke which exceeded their Fault. [See my Book of Forgiving Enemies.]</p>
               <p n="8">8. Do you <hi>do good to them that hate you?</hi> Do you conſider, that, to <hi>revenge</hi> your ſelves, is but <hi>to be even</hi> with Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies? To <hi>forgive</hi> them, is but to <hi>get above them.</hi> But, to do good for their Evil, is <hi>to riſe up to your Saviour's Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample.</hi> What think you of bleſſed <hi>Cran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> that ſtill was uneaſy, till he had anſwered an Affront with a Courteſy? And, an ill turn, with ſome good Gift! Pleaſe you, Sirs, to remember very <hi>Pericles,</hi> when a ſcurrilous Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low had railed againſt him all Day, he commanded his Footman to light him home at Night. And <hi>Lycurgus,</hi> that forgave with his Heart, the Man that ſtruck out one of his Eyes.</p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>Do you intreat your Tenants to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member their Landlord and yours?</hi> What! would not your intreaties make them pray daily with their Families? Make
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:65288:60"/>them <hi>read God's Word,</hi> as conſtantly as they eat his Bread? Make them as ſurely <hi>get their Children catechiſed,</hi> as clothed? Know you not, that your Words be of Power, to perfume their Cottages, with the Holy Word, and Prayer? And, that it is much from your ſilence, they are kept ſtinking with Vice, and rotting in Wickedneſs? Do not you, as others, mind no more than <hi>your own Rent;</hi> and ſhew no care of <hi>God's Tribute,</hi> or of your Tenants future State?</p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>Do you covet to be rich in good Works?</hi> Do you beſtow your Charity, <hi>extenſively;</hi> as the Sun its Light? <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily,</hi> as Fountains do their Waters; <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionably to what you have,</hi> as Clouds do their Rain; <hi>chearfully,</hi> as you do lay out ſpare Money on a rich Purchaſe? Are you of his Heart that profeſſeth; if Almſgiving were as <hi>ſweet to other Men as to him, they would rather cut the Fleſh of their Arms into ſlices, than give no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing?</hi> Do you regard your Saviour's Engagement and Encouragement? <hi>Give Alms, and behold all things are clean unto you!</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:65288:61"/>
               <p>Sirs, upon you it lies, to vindicate the Credit of <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> And to practiſe what you hear preached; St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Faith, which works by Love. St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>'s Faith, that ſhews it ſelf in brotherly Kindneſs and Charity. St. <hi>James</hi>'s Faith which hath Works to ſhew. St. <hi>Jude</hi>'s Faith, which is not a Cloud without Rain, or a Tree without Fruit. And St. <hi>John</hi>'s Faith, which is not in Word only, but in Deed and Truth: without which your Faith is a <hi>Peacock's Feather,</hi> your Hope is a <hi>Spider's Web,</hi> your Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is a <hi>painted Fire.</hi> You have much more Water than will turn your Mills. And, you have a Monitor in your Breaſts, that bids you not let any run, as the Waters of <hi>Jordan,</hi> into the <hi>dead Sea.</hi> Awake thou that ſleepeſt, preach this, O Conſcience! For in reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their own Mercy, Men do forfeit God's Mercy. Biſhop <hi>Burnet</hi>'s Letters ſay that the <hi>Annunciata</hi> in <hi>Naples,</hi> is the greateſt Hoſpital in the World. And, another tells us that, at <hi>Venice</hi> there are <hi>Seventy three rich Hoſpitals.</hi> The <hi>Dutch,</hi> all Men ſay, have <hi>no Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar</hi> among them. And Sir <hi>Thomas Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:65288:61"/>ſaith as much of the <hi>Chineſe.</hi> But, if Engliſh Nobles and Gentlemen, would but do as <hi>Thevenot</hi> reports of the <hi>Muſſelmen;</hi> would they give <hi>a ſeventh part</hi> of their Eſtates to the relief of the Poor; yea, or <hi>but a tenth part;</hi> it would be ſaid for Charity, <hi>Who is like thee O</hi> England?</p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>Do you abhor Prodigality; and the more for the ſake of Charity?</hi> Are you moderate in your Expences for Building and Furniture? For Apparel and Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainments. In the Year 85, <hi>the Pope of Rome,</hi> ſpent but <hi>a Crown</hi> a Day; and <hi>Siſto the</hi> 8th, exceeded not <hi>Eighteen-pence.</hi> Do you (who paſs for better Chriſtians) take care how you lay out the Money, whereof you are but Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards? Do you always, conſult your King, and Judg, whoſe it is? Do you deſpiſe a <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> drinking a Pearl of ſeventy eight thouſand Pound? And, a <hi>Lollia Paulina,</hi> wearing as many about her, as came to three hundred thouſand Pound? And, a <hi>Publicus Clodius,</hi> that muſt live in a Houſe which coſt an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and fourteen thouſand Pound? Plenty, without great Wiſdom, carries
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:65288:62"/>to wantonneſs and extravagance. When <hi>Rome</hi> ſwell'd with Wealth, it burſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to exceſs of both. More was given for a Fiſh, than would have bought an Ox. And, upon their <hi>Shooes</hi> they wore <hi>Pearls.</hi> Your Tympany may not riſe ſo high. But, under favour, be it asked; do you hate both extreams; of being profuſe, as the Sea, and of heaping up Gold as the Sand?</p>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>Do you preach to your ſelves that Goſpel Precept, Be ye courteous?</hi> Do you doubt but it binds the greateſt that are born of Women? You do not queſtion but it doth, and you cannot but feel, that, high Places do make rugged Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers. The <hi>Rich are anſwered roughly.</hi> Do you therefore well conſider; wilful Moroſity is extream Inhumanity. Nor have Saints <hi>ſufficient Grace,</hi> to bear ſo <hi>brutiſh a Nature.</hi> Do not ſpit upon this homeſpun Epithet! For, none is more true or apt. The <hi>African Foreſts</hi> have nothing more unreaſonable in them than thoſe <hi>Churls,</hi> who do brow-beat Men, made in the Image of God; and for no other Cauſe, than their want of gay <hi>Clothes.</hi> Who deſpiſe ſuch Men, as God
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:65288:62"/>hath honoured with the <hi>Righteouſneſs of his Son;</hi> with the <hi>Grace of his Spirit;</hi> with <hi>the Guard of his Angels;</hi> and with the <hi>Reverſion of his Heavenly Kingdom.</hi> And, this becauſe they have not to ſhew the <hi>Trophies of Moth and Ruſt, and Thieves.</hi> Can they tell us, why their Eyes do not rather deſpiſe their <hi>Ears,</hi> becauſe they have not the faculty of <hi>Seeing?</hi> And, their <hi>Ears,</hi> deſpiſe their <hi>Eyes,</hi> becauſe they have as little the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of <hi>Hearing?</hi> Do you not ſee it, Sirs, your poor Friends haſten from you, when they ſee lowring Faces, thô you have open Hands. <hi>Affability</hi> is as ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging as <hi>Money;</hi> and Charity it ſelf is odious, when it is moroſe. As Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, tho ever ſo wholeſome, when they are bitter they are loathſome. To give <hi>large Morſels,</hi> and not ſhew <hi>ſweet Manners,</hi> is to give Marrowhones with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Marrow in them. <hi>David,</hi> thô a King, who had been provoked, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gared his words; <hi>My People and my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi> 1 Chron. 28.2. The greater is your ſhame if you treat your <hi>fellow Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects</hi> with Language <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nhandſome. And, the rather, becauſe, right well you know,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:65288:63"/>that <hi>hard Words</hi> and <hi>ſowr Faces,</hi> like <hi>Spaniſh Flies,</hi> do raiſe Bliſters.</p>
               <p n="13">13. <hi>Do you make your Light to ſhine before Men?</hi> Good Works muſt not be done, to be ſeen of Men; <hi>to fetch in their Praiſes.</hi> But they muſt be done to be ſeen of Men; <hi>to carry them forth Patterns!</hi> Believe you not, that you are commanded ſo to do them, that Friends and Enemies may be compelled to ſee them? You know, your Sins are written in Letters big enough for them to read. And, think you, that your Duties to God, and your Neighbour, ſhould be drawn in a leſs Character? Of old, <hi>the Angel was a Deſtroyer, if the Blood of the Lamb was not ſeen on the Door.</hi> Works and not Words, muſt convince Men that you are <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> and that you do value no <hi>Birth,</hi> like the Second; no <hi>Eſtate,</hi> like the Saints In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance in Light; no Place of <hi>Honour,</hi> like Chriſt's right Hand; no <hi>Place of Power,</hi> like that of judging the World; and no <hi>State,</hi> like the Heavenly one, in which, Deſires are exceeded, and Fears excluded! Ought you not to convince Men hereof? Or, think you, that any
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:65288:63"/>Language, but the language of Practice can convince them?</p>
               <p n="14">14. Do you <hi>greatly fear the leaſt Sin?</hi> Do you keep in Mind, what you well know? That, an everlaſting Hell, is the <hi>Wages</hi> of the leaſt Sin! That, St. <hi>Paul</hi> cried, <hi>O wretched Man,</hi> for very involuntary Sin! That, the old Law re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired Sacrifice for <hi>Sin in a very Dream,</hi> Lev. 15.16. That, it did alſo require <hi>extraordinary Sacrifices,</hi> for <hi>great</hi> Mens Sins. (Signifying your Treaſons to be <hi>the higher</hi> for being <hi>yours.</hi>) That the leaſt ſpark of Sin quickly becomes a great Flame! He, who was tempted to <hi>kill his Father, to defile his Mother, and to make himſelf drunk;</hi> he refuſed the two firſt, but promptly complied with the laſt. And, what came of it? Why, having glibly ſwallowed his one <hi>Gnat;</hi> before he came to himſelf again, he took down the <hi>two Camels</hi> alſo. If you will let in ever ſo little Thieves, the <hi>Pygmies</hi> will open your Doors to <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kims.</hi> A vain Thought, invites in the Sin againſt the Holy Ghoſt. When it is indulged, and favoured, it doth ſo.</p>
               <p n="15">
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:65288:64"/>15. Do you, of all Sins, <hi>dread the Thought of turning Grace into Wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs?</hi> Of ſinning, becauſe Grace a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds? Of being ready to ſin, becauſe God is ready to forgive? Of daring to take down <hi>ſweet Poiſon,</hi> becauſe a <hi>pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful Antidote</hi> is prepared by your Soul's Phyſician? It is unqueſtionably true; the <hi>Forgiving great Sins is God's great Praiſe.</hi> Your Unrighteouſneſs, in his way of pardoning it, ſets off God's Righteouſneſs; and eminently praiſes it. But, what then? Of them that ſay, <hi>Let us do evil, that good may come;</hi> the Herald of free Grace ſaith plainly; <hi>Their Damnation is juſt!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is told you by a moſt miſtaken Man, if theſe following particulars, be not too much forgotten, by <hi>Lords and Ladies.</hi> There is no Alliance between <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Belial.</hi> Imputed Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, thô it <hi>frees from Hell;</hi> it doth not, without inherent Righteouſneſs, <hi>capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citate for Heaven.</hi> Lepers, would be Lepers in the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> it ſelf. 'Tis not the <hi>Place</hi> that can impart Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs. You cannot be like God in Felicity, if you be not like him in Purity.
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:65288:64"/>But, there can be no <hi>greater Sin,</hi> than the abuſe of Grace. No greater <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluity of Naughtineſs,</hi> than miſuſe of Mercy and Forgiveneſs. Nothing can render you ſo unworthy of Mercy, as ſinning upon the Preſumption of it. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſays it was this, that aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated <hi>Judas</hi> his Sin, and kept him from hope of Pardon!</p>
               <p n="16">16. Do you <hi>know thorowly how to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound?</hi> i. e. To perform the Duties, and to avoid the Dangers of your Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity. The great Apoſtle and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr of Chriſt did know this. And the Prince of Pagan Philoſophers and Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers, <hi>boaſted</hi> of his knowing it. Tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the World, that, <hi>he always kept a great diſtance between himſelf and his Eſtate.</hi> Inſomuch, that, <hi>When he came to part with it, it came off eaſily, as a Glove from his Hand; not, with torture, as his Skin from his Fleſh.</hi> Sirs, do you keep this diſtance, and greater? Do you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that you are but <hi>Men?</hi> For <hi>Iron Fanes</hi> are not Gold, but Iron, tho they be ſet upon ever ſo high Steeples. And <hi>Dwarfs</hi> are but Dwarfs, tho they do ſtand upon ever ſo high Stilts. Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der you, that, being <hi>great Men,</hi> you
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:65288:65"/>have greater Duties incumbent on you? And, the greater are the Sins, which are committed by you. Conſider you, that, being alſo <hi>new Men,</hi> the Holy Ghoſt is extreamly grieved by your Miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages? Unregenerate Mens Sins <hi>reſiſt,</hi> and <hi>vex;</hi> but yours do alſo <hi>grieve</hi> him. In ſhort; they muſt <hi>have an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction from the Holy one, and know all things,</hi> who do truly know how to <hi>uſe this World's good things.</hi> Tho every <hi>Abcdari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> be apt to turn a <hi>Pygmalion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="17">17. <hi>Do you owe nothing but what you haſten to pay?</hi> No Reſpect, no good Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, no Money? The <hi>Divine old Law,</hi> is in force upon the Higheſt of you; <hi>At his Day thou ſhalt give the poor Hireling his Hire; neither ſhall the Sun go down on it; leſt he cry to the Lord, and it be Sin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee.</hi> The <hi>Civilians Maxim</hi> is at your Tongues ends, againſt tardy-pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Tenants; <hi>Minùs ſolvit qui minus tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore ſolvit.</hi> Sum-total is no <hi>good Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> if it be not brought in <hi>good Time.</hi> And, this holds as to all Debts. Inſomuch, that the <hi>Cries of Tradeſmen</hi> are horrible <hi>Reproaches to Gentlemen.</hi> And, you your ſelves do raiſe the worſt <hi>Scandala Magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> when you ſuffer <hi>Mercers</hi> and <hi>Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors</hi>
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:65288:65"/>to come, and pull you by <hi>their own Coats.</hi> (Coats, that be theirs, and not yours, till they are paid for.) When you let <hi>Butchers, Poulterers,</hi> and <hi>Fiſhmongers</hi> have it to ſay, <hi>That your Tables are their Snares.</hi> Making hundreds to complain, that by <hi>arraying</hi> your ſelves, you reduce them unto <hi>Nakedneſs;</hi> and by your <hi>Feaſting,</hi> you do bring them to <hi>Famine.</hi> That they had not <hi>failed,</hi> if you had not <hi>broken them.</hi> When, likewiſe, your Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick Servants are made to ſerve <hi>half an Apprenticeſhip,</hi> before they receive a <hi>Year's Wages.</hi> Sirs; the <hi>greateſt Men in Jeruſalem,</hi> were threatned to be made <hi>Bondmen,</hi> for <hi>unkindneſs to their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,</hi> Jer. 34th. And, <hi>Jehojakim</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf is meant, in that word of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet; <hi>Wo to him that uſeth his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour without Wages. Delaying</hi> of Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment moſt times maketh <hi>diminution;</hi> and, many times <hi>utter denial</hi> of it.</p>
               <p>Be it asked alſo, by the way; what your Worſhips think of this, whereof you do hear leſs? Leſs, from your <hi>Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains,</hi> and leſs from your <hi>Conſciences.</hi> Is it no Sin, or but a Peccadillo, <hi>to let a Servant go away from you empty?</hi> Shift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:65288:66"/>and deſtitute of means to live from you. What? Is the Law repeal'd which ſaith expreſly concerning a departing Servant? <hi>Thou ſhalt furniſh him libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally out of thy Flock, and out of thy Floor, and out of thy Winepreſs. Of that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the Lord thy God hath bleſſed thee, thou ſhalt give unto him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Away with paltry excuſes! <hi>Iſraelites</hi> are not <hi>themſelves</hi> when they turn off an <hi>old Servant,</hi> with leſs Proviſion made for him, than what is made for an <hi>old Horſe</hi> or <hi>Hound!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wherein you have done Iniquity, good</hi> Sirs, <hi>do no more!</hi> But, repent, reſtore, reform, and <hi>let your Zeal provoke many!</hi> That, <hi>Men of Eſtates,</hi> and <hi>Beaſts of Prey,</hi> may no longer be <hi>Synonymous Terms,</hi> and the <hi>ſame Things!</hi> That it may no more be ſaid, you are fell as <hi>Lions,</hi> fierce as <hi>Leopards,</hi> ſavage as <hi>Bears,</hi> ravenous as <hi>Wolves,</hi> and that under a Form of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs. No, but that, you are together <hi>Gentle</hi> and <hi>Noblemen. Nurſing Fathers</hi> to your poor Neighbours; <hi>uſeful Elms</hi> to bear up all the weak and needy Vines, which are near you; <hi>ſweet Springs,</hi> to them, that have not Water enough to keep their Mills going.</p>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:65288:66"/>
               <p>It will one day be more honour, to have enabled a poor Man to <hi>keep his Cart on the Wheels,</hi> than to have kept ſeven of your <hi>own Coaches and Chariots</hi> on them. And, alas, what Pillows do you ſleep on, in the mean time; you, who cannot challenge the Town, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, as <hi>Samuel</hi> did; <hi>Whom have I defraud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, whom have I oppreſſed?</hi> Who cannot appeal, as the Prince, and the Saint of the Land of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>Z; Have I deſpiſed the Cauſe of my Man-ſervant or Maid-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, when they contended with me? Have I withheld the Poor their deſire, or cauſed the Eyes of the Widow to fail? Have I eaten my Morſel alone? and the Fatherleſs not eaten thereof? Have I ſeen any to periſh for want of Clothing, or any Poor without Covering? Have I lifted up my Hand againſt the Fatherleſs, when I ſaw my help in the Gate?</hi> What think you of your ſelves, you, who cannot ſay as <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; I have not hurt any one!</hi> And, as St. <hi>Paul; I have coveted no Man's Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, Gold, or Apparel!</hi> Yea, and as <hi>our Saviour,</hi> our grand Exemplar; <hi>I have done many good Works among you!</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:65288:67"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Clerks of your Cloſets,</hi> are not true unto God or your Souls, if they put you not in remembrance of theſe things. And, preach not <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Mercy.</hi> They can tell you if they pleaſe of the <hi>Sultan Selymus;</hi> who being preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by his <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> to lay out upon <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitals,</hi> what he had wrongfully taken from the <hi>Perſians,</hi> abhorred it. And, required that it ſhould be reſtored, all of it, to the right Owners. And, with your good leave, they are able to add; that, <hi>Except the Righteouſneſs of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Gentleman, exceed the Righteouſneſs of a Turkiſh Sultan, he is not very likely to enter the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="18">18. <hi>Do you ſtudy the Book of Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes?</hi> You, <hi>more than others,</hi> are in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of being poiſoned. And, ſhould you not <hi>more than others,</hi> acquaint your ſelves with the Antidote? Riches, tho an <hi>adored Idol,</hi> are a <hi>ſtrong Poiſon.</hi> Whom of you do they do not make <hi>to ſwell,</hi> more or leſs? And, throughout the <hi>Royal Diſpenſatory</hi> you find not ſuch ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Antidote as in <hi>this praiſed Book.</hi> Should you not, therefore, give it good Reading? One of your Rank made his
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:65288:67"/>thirteen Children, learn the <hi>Proverbs of Solomon</hi> by heart. I would that more of you would both learn and teach the Book of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There you are told, your <hi>Cains</hi> are but <hi>Abels,</hi> i. e. Your <hi>Poſſeſſions</hi> be but <hi>Vanities.</hi> Your <hi>Riches</hi> do fill but your <hi>Mouths,</hi> not your <hi>Appetites.</hi> You have as many <hi>unſatisfied Deſires,</hi> as the <hi>People that rake Cinders.</hi> Your <hi>Titles</hi> may over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge your <hi>Memories,</hi> but can never fill your <hi>Pride.</hi> Your <hi>ſenſual Pleaſures</hi> may waſte your Spirits, and ſtupify your Senſes, but can never ſatisfy, and make them ſay, <hi>it is enough.</hi> You are told of all the three; that, as many other Drugs, they are <hi>deadly without due Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectives.</hi> That, as all Flowers, they do fade quickly; and the longer you poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs them, the leſs they do <hi>delight you.</hi> However, that, they neither <hi>prevent</hi> or <hi>retard</hi> Death. But do frequently <hi>haſten</hi> Diſeaſes and Death. That they are as diſproportionate to the Wants of your Souls, as ſhadows are to the Wants of your Bodies. That, (as you have it ſaid of your Children) <hi>they are certain Cares, and uncertain Comforts.</hi> And, that by
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:65288:68"/>all your Chymiſtry, you ſhall never ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract Satisfaction out of them! No, but be far from any true <hi>Peace</hi> in the uſe of them, without theſe <hi>Anodynes,</hi> viz.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Religious Content with your Quota.</hi> Neither <hi>vexing</hi> that you have no more, nor <hi>envying</hi> to ſee others have Meaſure preſſed down and running over. It was moſt truly that <hi>Seneca</hi> told his <hi>Lucilius;</hi> it is Luſt that is ſick for <hi>Houſe fulls;</hi> Nature is as well with a few <hi>Spoonfuls.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chearful and Thankful uſe of your Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,</hi> according to the Quality of your <hi>Degree,</hi> the Decency of your <hi>Condition,</hi> and the Rules of <hi>Religion.</hi> Without luxurious Exceeding, or ſordid Living.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Humble acquieſcence under every Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</hi> Being dumb, whatever God doth, becauſe he doth it. He, whoſe Will is your Law. And, whoſe Gifts are more common than Day-light; but his Strokes, more rare than Thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhots.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Spirit, and Truth in God's Holy Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</hi> Service paid to his Majeſty, with all your Heart, and by the Rule of his Word. For <hi>bodily Service profits not.</hi> And, what is not preſcribed by the
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:65288:68"/>Divine Canon, is no better than <hi>a Dog's Neck. Regular Service and ſincere, is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Freedom;</hi> and <hi>profitable to all things.</hi> But <hi>God hath no pleaſure in Fools.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sedateneſs of Mind under Oppreſſions by Men.</hi> Poſſeſſion of your Soul in Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, while your <hi>Subſtance</hi> is ſmitten with the firſt of Wickedneſs. And, your <hi>Name,</hi> with the tyrannous <hi>Tongue</hi> of it. Imitation of your grand Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plar; <hi>who was oppreſſed, and opened not his Mouth.</hi> Did not lay any Fewel on his Oppreſſors Fire. Did not call them <hi>Devils,</hi> who told him <hi>he was a</hi> Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, <hi>and had a Devil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A prepared Breaſt for all Events.</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared as <hi>Pilgrims</hi> ſhould be, for Calms, and Storms. Prepared, to receive <hi>ſweet</hi> things <hi>thankfully;</hi> and <hi>bitter</hi> ones <hi>pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently.</hi> Moſt certain it is, that, he is Proof for any thing, that is become wiſe enough to prefer <hi>Preſervation in Brine,</hi> above <hi>Corruption in Honey.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prudent Deport and Behaviour towards all Men.</hi> The Wiſdom of the Serpent, with the Innocence of the Dove, is a neceſſary Ingredient in human Life. A <hi>natural</hi> force it hath, and an <hi>inſtituted</hi>
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:65288:69"/>one; to preſerve Names from Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and Perſons from Injury. It puts to ſilence the Ignorance of fooliſh Men. And, wins the very <hi>ſpiteful,</hi> unto Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. For, moſt of them be found tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctable, when they are diſcreetly taken by the right Handle.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charity towards the worſt of Men.</hi> Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity that <hi>believes</hi> all things, <hi>bears</hi> all things, <hi>hopes</hi> all things, <hi>endures</hi> all things. Charity that not only ſuffers, but is <hi>kind;</hi> and is not eaſily <hi>provoked.</hi> Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which abhors that condemned word, <hi>I will do unto the Man, as he hath done unto me!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sobriety, or juſt Government of the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections toward ſenſual things.</hi> Things, whoſe <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> is neceſſary; but, the <hi>Exceſs</hi> is deadly. And, therefore, Affections toward them muſt be <hi>moderated,</hi> not <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed.</hi> Cynical Auſterity, is <hi>Phrenzy</hi> more than <hi>Piety.</hi> But, Intemperance is a more common, and open defiance of Righteouſneſs, and Holineſs. The Vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals hereof do <hi>rob God</hi> of their <hi>Hearts and Lives.</hi> Rob <hi>themſelves</hi> of their <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings.</hi> Rob <hi>Church and State</hi> of their <hi>Service.</hi> Rob <hi>their Families</hi> of
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:65288:69"/>their <hi>Maintenance.</hi> Thus doth every Soul, that is under the power of Wine and Oil!</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Practick Prudence.</hi> Which is more than Science or <hi>Knowledg of the Natures of things. A Skill it is, to diſpoſe of them for good.</hi> To take the right <hi>Way</hi> and <hi>Seaſon,</hi> to convert them to the beſt Uſes. A Skill, without which, Science makes you but like a uſeleſs Ship. One, which hath a <hi>Sail,</hi> but of no uſe; as wanting a <hi>Rudder</hi> to direct its Courſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pious Loyalty.</hi> Obedience to the <hi>King's Laws</hi> as far as conſiſteth with the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Commandments.</hi> Obedience to them as free and as full, as that which your <hi>Hands</hi> and <hi>Feet</hi> do yield to your <hi>Head.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Juſt Diligence.</hi> For, by much Sloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs very <hi>lofty Buildings</hi> will decay. Thrô the Idleneſs of noble Hands <hi>Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Cedar</hi> will drop through. One <hi>Hebrew</hi> word ſignifies, both, a <hi>rich Man,</hi> and a <hi>Man at Eaſe.</hi> But, to be idle, is the direct way to get rid of <hi>Riches</hi> and Eaſe. He that <hi>ſees</hi> all things by his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants <hi>Eyes,</hi> and <hi>doeth</hi> all by their <hi>Hands;</hi> hath, commonly, both his <hi>Eyes to wipe,</hi> and his <hi>Hands to wring,</hi> before he is much
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:65288:70"/>older. It is not for <hi>Lords</hi> or very <hi>Kings</hi> to eat <hi>the Bread of Idleneſs.</hi> Tho they are not to <hi>ſweep the Houſe,</hi> or <hi>plow the Field;</hi> they are to <hi>know the ſtate of their Flocks, and to look well unto their Herds.</hi> Idleneſs exempts the higheſt of Men from the protection of Angels, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.11. Without ſome Pains no <hi>Infant</hi> ſucks. And, it is againſt God's Command, that any <hi>grown Body</hi> ems, unleſs he works, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.8.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Much Giving and Forgiving.</hi> You may come your ſelves, to Bread and Water, if you <hi>caſt not your Bread upon the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</hi> i. e. If you <hi>give not Portions to ſeven, and alſo to eight;</hi> to <hi>Waters,</hi> or to multitudes of People; numberleſs as Water-drops. And, if you will <hi>give heed to all that is ſpoken;</hi> if you will not wink at ſome Faults, and paſs by ſome Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages, you will make your Servants <hi>curſe you to your Faces.</hi> i.e. By being <hi>mercileſs</hi> you will make them <hi>deſperate.</hi> If you are ſo <hi>unlike God</hi> toward them, you will have them very <hi>like Devils</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Holy Root and Fruit.</hi> The Root of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Reverence, the Fruit of univerſal
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:65288:70"/>Obedience. <hi>Fearing God, and keeping his Commandments.</hi> To wit, in the Faith of Chriſt, without whom we can do nothing! And the God with whom we have to do, will accept of nothing. Theſe are the <hi>whole</hi> of Man, or <hi>all</hi> of a Man. His <hi>Nature,</hi> his <hi>Duty,</hi> and his <hi>Intereſt,</hi> ſaith the great Biſhop <hi>Wilkins!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In ſhort; <hi>Courts</hi> as well <hi>Cottages,</hi> are ſummoned to attend theſe things. <hi>Let <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S hear the Concluſion of the whole Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> And, you, as well as we, are preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with a double Argument. From the <hi>Comprehenſiveneſs of the Matter,</hi> and from the <hi>Exactneſs of God's Judgment.</hi> The Judgment into which <hi>God will bring every OPEN Work and SECRET, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be Good or Evil!</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The Concluſion.</head>
               <p>SIRS, What hath been <hi>delivered</hi> to you, hath been <hi>received</hi> from your Lord, and ours.</p>
               <p>It will be no new thing, if the <hi>Beaux Eſprits</hi> do laugh it to ſcorn. If one and
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:65288:71"/>another <hi>Naaman</hi> do deſpiſe <hi>Jordan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Phreneticks do uſe to throw away the <hi>Medicine,</hi> and trample on the <hi>Plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> which would heal them. Who knows not what <hi>Stones were caſt</hi> at the Prince of Preach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs, our very Saviour? <hi>Lepers,</hi> were never fond of <hi>Looking-glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and <hi>Madmen</hi> never loved <hi>Hellebore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> they were never ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>forward Converts!</hi> An un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ring Judg ſaith it; <hi>Publicans and Harlots</hi> are leſs obſtinate. Morally, as well as Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, we ſee, that <hi>Conſumptions do kill more than Calentures.</hi> Moſt People do periſh under one or other <hi>form of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs.</hi> And, of the two, there be few<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, who do caſt themſelves <hi>headlong</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Tophet,</hi> than do deſcend <hi>ſtep by ſtep</hi> into it.</p>
               <p>Neither is it to be denied, but, that, <hi>Spots are hardly got out of Diamonds too.</hi> And much Sope and Nitre, are loſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on many a Holy Creature. Our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's <hi>two rebukes</hi> of an undoubted Saint, prevented not a <hi>third out breach</hi> of the ſelf ſame Sin. <hi>Get thee behind me Satan,</hi> one would have thought, ſhould have been Refining Fire in his Heart. <hi>The
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:65288:71"/>Cock's crowing,</hi> which ſet him bitterly weeping, might have been expected to have ſufficiently warned him againſt <hi>haſty ſpeaking.</hi> But, no ſuch matter; out again it brake; <hi>What ſhall this Man do?</hi> In ſhort; the beſt Chriſtians do ſtill remain too <hi>Legal,</hi> thô they read much the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> and <hi>Galatians.</hi> And, too too <hi>Licentious,</hi> thô they do read the Epiſtles of St. <hi>James,</hi> St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and St. <hi>Jude!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs; in <hi>Duty</hi> unto all, and in <hi>Hope</hi> of ſome of you; <hi>Whether you will hear, or whether you will forbear,</hi> this Trumpet is blown.</p>
               <p>Their <hi>Smart</hi> it is, and <hi>Pain;</hi> not <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal</hi> and <hi>Pride,</hi> which maketh diſeaſed and wounded Creatures to <hi>curvet</hi> and <hi>prance.</hi> And, it is <hi>pure Compaſſion,</hi> wherewith I ſhall follow <hi>the moſt inſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Scorners</hi> of my Counſel. I have conſulted <hi>ſurer Oracles,</hi> than thoſe of <hi>Dodona,</hi> and <hi>Delphos.</hi> And am perfectly certain of thus much;</p>
               <p>That, very many of you <hi>Fat upon the Earth,</hi> as well as the Poor <hi>that go down to the Duſt,</hi> Pſal. 22.29. Many of you <hi>Grandees</hi> muſt one day be <hi>Converts.</hi>
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:65288:72"/>That, the very <hi>Wolves</hi> of you ſhall come into the Fellowſhip of the Goſpel with our <hi>Saviour's Lambs.</hi> That, the <hi>Leopards ſhall lie down with Kids; Calves, young Lions, and Fatlings toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and a little Child ſhall lead you,</hi> Iſa. 11.6, 9. An <hi>humble Miniſter,</hi> of no more State than a newly weaned Child, ſhall manage you as well as <hi>a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Lord!</hi> And, you ſhall <hi>no more hurt or deſtroy in all</hi> God's Holy Mountain. No, but,</p>
               <p>You, <hi>Mountains,</hi> of the Nobility, <hi>ſhall bring Peace to the People;</hi> and you the <hi>little Hills of</hi> the Gentry, alſo, <hi>by Righteouſneſs,</hi> Pſal. 72.3. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:65288:72"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
